Radio.com
The modern world doesn't acknowledge, but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons.
and saints. In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism
to see and to know reality as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage
with it well? How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests,
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young host this live Colin show focused on
Enchantment in creation the union of the scene
and unseen as made by God and experienced by mankind throughout history. Welcome to the Lord of
Spirits. Good evening, giant killers, dragon slayers, serpent and scorpion stompers. You are
listening to Lord of Spirits podcast, my co-host, the very Reverend, almost double doctor,
Father Stephen D. Young is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana. I'm Father Intersteem and D. Amick,
in a mass Pennsylvania with considerably fewer academic degrees.
If you're listening to us live, you can call in at 855 AF radio.
That's 855-237-2346.
And Mattress Kachuri is back on the job tonight.
Taking your calls, we're going to get to those in the second part of our show.
And of course, Elijah just disappeared.
Perhaps he's taken up.
Poor Elijah.
You can go back Elijah.
Everything is fine.
We want your back.
We've got this open share for you.
Yeah.
Tonight we're going to continue.
consider, consider, well consider continuing our series on eschatology with the dawn of the
year 2000 just 23 years in the rear view mirror.
It just makes me feel a little like I'm shriveling a little bit.
Yeah.
Boat is turning to powder.
It might seem like the much prophesied millennium bug is old hat.
I also remember the house on days of 2012 when we were told that the Mayan calendar had reached
its
spicy end. Yet the millennium remains an element to Christian theology because it's in the Bible.
Funny how that works. So that's what we're going to talk about tonight. What exactly is this millennium?
Why do the British like to say world without end at the end of their prayers? A lot of people
have been wondering that a bit. What is the ancient heresy of kiliasum? And is it true that St.
and the church swept that under the rug
or just had a general agreement.
not to talk about it. So no. Man spoilers, dude. It's not until
third half. Oh, okay. Sorry. Sorry. I guess we got to make
sure we hold everybody's attention. Yeah, we don't startle
anybody. It's true. We're talking about how old we are. Pearl
clutching. See, you're curious. Wasn't to kill you. Yes. I mean,
we're, we're Jen extras though. So like, are we even allowed to
to talk about our feelings about the millennium.
No, there are only two appropriate things to do with feelings.
Number one is to tamp and stomp them down until they build up pressure and you explode like a volcano destroying everything around you
or to drown them in hard liquor until there is dead as you are inside.
Wow, we're gonna get emails about that one.
That one, there we go.
Like you're always like, I'm gonna get canceled for this, I'm gonna get this.
No, it's gonna be that.
It's gonna be that that I'm gonna get the emails.
emails last last episode.
it was the the great online pasta wars of 2023.
I think that that may have spawned more comments than any other like throw a comment.
And this week it's going to be my my tongue in cheek or was it anti feelings?
But getting very Dutch right from the get go.
Yes. So yeah, some say the end is near. Some say we'll see Armageddon soon.
but uh
We've been told a lot of lies about the Millennium.
I don't know if you remember back in the year 2000.
One will deferred Albert Smith told us all that this was going to be the will
in him.
Wow.
I don't remember that.
I mean, I remember Will Smith, but yeah, that hasn't panned out so well.
Right.
For him.
uh... there was a robby william song
Yes, about millennium as well. Yes, but I don't.
Lance Hendricksons, the hair turned white. Yeah.
Also in the year 2012, we were told by John Qsac that you can flee the crumbling earth in a
winnow bago successfully. I mean, so techs up. No, I think that is also a lie.
That's what more you povich told me at least.
Thanks.
So that way we have more e-pobits to tell us these things.
Yes.
Oh, if you want to find out if the baby's yours or if someone is lying, you go to more e-pobits.
That's it.
Yeah.
People in Judy Cave.
He would never lie to us.
All such matters.
Yeah.
And he's married to Connie Chunk, like what?
You know.
If you can't trust Connie Chunk, can you trust?
Well.
You know what?
There's so many people I could trust in front of Connie.
Anyway, yes, Millennium. Yes. What are we talking about again? Yeah. Yeah. The Millennium. And so
You know the main place in scripture
That talks about the Millennium as such is Revelation chapter 20
Yeah, so as is our want we'll be talking about that dead last at the end of the show as one does
But until then
We're gonna be laying groundwork as again is our want
Um.
So we're going to start with the whole concept of an age in scripture because ultimately
what the millennium is is an age.
And so before we can get to that particular age, we have to understand the concept of an age
in general. And the most common way in which an age
is referred to in the Hebrew Bible is with the term day, yom.
And so just connecting the idea of day and age, I know has triggered a bunch of young earth
creationists, but that's not where we're going. So we're like, I think we lost them a long time
ago, honestly. That may be, but that's not where we're going with this at all. Right. So,
But the word day in addition
to just referring to a day, right? It does sometimes, the Hebrew Bible just refer to a 24-hour period
or to the daylight hours, like day, night, right? But there are also more specialized
usages of it. So when you see day with the definite article, so hyom, or V-day,
as it's usually translated in English,
that is in most cases a reference to the day of the Lord.
The day of Yahweh.
Yeah.
When God shows up and puts everything right.
Right.
He visits his people and settles things.
And things are resolved.
So this is true, by the way, that we're not
Here we go, two deep in.
into this now. This is true also in Genesis 3. There's that weird phrase that gets translated
at all kinds of weird contradictory ways in English is like the heat of the day, right?
Got you going to the heat of the day or the wind of the day or the cool of the afternoon
or I can translate it all these. What it literally says there is Ruakha Yom, the spirit of
the day.
And God comes walking after Adam and Eve have transgressed and he comes walking in the spirit of the day.
So this is deliberately in the Hebrew you've voking the idea of judgment.
Right? And that's what's happening.
This is sort of an early intrusion.
Right. Of the, of course, the day of the Lord, the day of Yahweh, right? The day is this pivotal,
transitional moment. Right. It is when we're talking about the day of Yahweh and the Hebrew
scriptures, we're talking about this transitional moment from one age to another.
That's why it's relevant here because as we're understanding the concept of an age in scripture,
Sure we are.
to not only understand that there are these ages, but that there are these pivotal and decisive
moments where things happen that inaugurate a new one, where there's passage into a new one.
And so, sometimes the Bible will use the same word to refer to the period, but also to that moment.
Right, right.
So, um...
Another way in which day, Yom is used in this, his reference to that day, right?
And that will be take the form in English translation of in that day, right?
And in that day can be sort of retrospective, right?
talking about the past, right? In that day.
right. The city of Dan was called Leish, right? Or it can be prospective. It could refer
to the future. In that day, no man will teach his brother, right? Saying, no, the Lord
right? Yeah. So, you know, the first one, like back in the day, as we say colloquially
English. Yeah, retrospectively. Yeah, back of the day, or in
my day kids. We didn't. Yeah, right. Express our emotions. Yeah. So you're triggering
a lot of people with that. It's okay. I already told them what to do with those feelings.
I'm triggering. Yeah. And so this is a reference to an age or an era, right? And it's referring
to it as a whole.
right? Just referring to it simply, right, that era, that time period, that age as a whole.
You also get the days of fill in the blank, right? So the days of Noah is a very common one in
Scripture. Yeah. Right? So for back to the days of Noah, meaning the period when Noah was alive,
right.
that it's taking that age or era and associating it with a particular person and through that person
with particular events and the life of that person, what is going on with that person,
the days of Sodom, the days of, and you can associate then an age in that way with a person,
with a concept. We do that poetically in English as well.
Well, like days of wine and roses, right?
These are the days of miracles and wonders.
This is the long distance call.
And it was nice.
Yeah.
That was the first cassette tape I ever owned.
There we go.
Yeah, it was Grace Landbite.
Digging in the Grace Landbite.
Yeah.
So yeah, so it's associating them then with this particular
character or characterization.
Right, connecting the age to that.
There's also in the phrase, in those days.
Right, and so you have in that day, using the singular and then you have in those days, which is plural.
And both of those are essentially the same kind of reference in that they're referring to a past or future age or era.
But when it's singular, it's sort of referring to it as a unit.
it, whereas when it's plural in those days, it's referring to it in terms of extent over
time.
Yeah, there's a plurality.
Yeah, and like, like the way that I kind of worked it out was in terms, I mean, this
is a rough analogy, in terms of grammar, like, so you've got the past perfect, you know,
at that time, you know, in that period, in that era, you know.
versus sort of past and perfect.
Like it used to be the case.
You know, it was ongoing, right?
And I mean, even when we just use the singular
article in English versus a plural one,
it can make a big difference.
Like we talk about the United States
versus the United States.
That's a different concept, you know.
And it's the sense of, and in this case,
plurality you know this
states altogether, whereas the United States is like a single unit that's one country.
Right. Yeah. And if people, if people have a little Greek, this is a difference between the
heirs and the imperfect and Greek. Yeah. So yeah. So this is, in that day might be used to refer
to something like, say the name of the city, and that day Dan was called Leish. Right.
It's just being used, that period is a whole...
to locate when you're talking about the city had that name.
Whereas when you get in those days, the plural to refer to the extent,
you're talking about how something was true over a period of time.
Yeah, right.
In those days.
There was no king. Everyone did what was right in his own eyes.
Yeah. Yeah.
Right.
So you have ongoing, right?
the idea that's being stressed there, either in the past or in the future.
So that's sort of the Hebrew use, and since that's centering around the word day, that
obviously is an analogical use of the word day that denotatively is referring to really
a 12-hour period, give or take, depending on time of year.
Yeah, I went to the
and you know, versus the night.
Right.
To, to refer to another time period,
which generally would have,
generally would be considered to have a beginning
and an end, right?
Yeah.
I mean, we do that with other units of time,
like we talk about something happening in a hot minute
or, you know, in that hour, such and such.
We don't mean in those 60 minutes or in those 60 seconds,
right?
It's, right.
Yeah, it's extended outwards to mean...
a period. Right. And hour is even used that way in Scripture. Right. Yeah.
Right. Saying, my hour has not yet come. Right. Right. It doesn't mean look, it's going to be a three 25.
Yeah. Two 425. Yeah. Yeah.
So in Greek, what we generally have for ages, A on. Right.
from which we get the English word Eon.
And A-O is usually literally translated age.
Right. Right.
And that's why we've been using the term age so far.
But age, obviously, I mean on the face of it,
when you talk about this age and then there's the next age,
and then there's the age to come, right.
That language, de facto, is a way of periodizing time.
Right, of taking time.
of its extent and dividing it into finite periods. Right? Say this age and then that age and
then the next age. Right? In the same way that you would, you know, you could take a desk and say,
all right, this is the left side of the desk. This is the middle of the desk. This is the right side
of the desk, right? You are dividing it, and in that sense, periodization can be...
arbitrary. So in the sense that you know we to use an example from time, right, we talk about, you know, oh, late antiquity, right, the dark ages, the middle ages.
Yes.
Yes, the early modern period.
Right.
And you can of course argue and publish journal articles about where exactly those begin
and end.
Were there even dark ages?
And...
right? Because those are somewhat arbitrary divisions based on various things. But the word A
on or A includes more than just the concept of a division of time. So that word conveys
more than that that takes it out of the realm of the arbitrary. Because ultimately...
it has the resonance of a particular order, a particular state of things that prevails for a period of time.
Right. And when the terms like middle ages, dark ages, the bronze age, the iron age, theolithic, right.
when these are you.
used quasi-scientifically in a scholarly manner, that's what they're actually being used
to refer to, not in arbitrary and over years, but a period during which a certain ordering
of the world prevailed.
Yeah, like Bronze Age is specifically about that metallurgical accomplishment and its
effects on civilization.
And there are certain political forms that prevailed during that period.
Yeah.
We talk about the end of the Bronze Age and the Bronze Age.
collapse, that was the collapse of a sort of world order that had developed during that period.
Yeah.
And then comes to an end.
And when we talk about late antiquity, it's late antiquity for a reason, the Western
Roman Empire is collapsing, right?
And there's a shift happening in the whole order of things.
And this is really include in this idea of Aeon.
It's a world order or state of things.
And so this then is
in Latin translation is where we get into the word Seculum.
And the word Seculum really conveyed that same kind of idea of a world order, right?
of a world structure. And St. Augustine really develops the way the word secularism is
used really elevates in terms of how that word is going to be understood going forward in the west
in city of God because he being being the Platonist he was
uses the sort of platonic schema of being and becoming and applies it to the city of God the sort of
of age in which God eternally exists.
on the one hand, and then on the other hand, on the earth, there is this constant sort of
churning and turning of one secular one order, one world into another. And that's very much
the point he's wanting to make in the city of God. He's like, yes, those of you who think
because the Western Roman Empire is collapsed.
that the world is ending, it sort of is in a way, right?
In a sense, that world, that ordering of things that had prevailed
until now for centuries is now dying and dead.
Yes.
All this has happened before and all this will happen again.
Right.
And now a new order will rise and that will continue to happen over and over and over again in this world.
while the age
above the age of which God dwells is eternal.
Yeah, which is then why?
I don't remember exactly how the phrase goes in Latin.
Is it Cecalus, Cecalodum?
Are my getting the grammar wrong?
Cecalus, Cecalodum.
I don't remember.
I have to look it up.
Which, you know, in Latin translates,
it's Tussionus, Donneon, from Greek,
which we usually translate into English
as unto ages of ages.
But that cyclosecachalorum...
And in some of the early modern English translations becomes world without end, world without end,
because it's the idea that it's a world without end versus these worlds upon worlds, you know,
one world after another that characterizes this world in the Augustine conception.
Right.
And that's going to have some consequences, right, that are relevant to what we're talking
about tonight.
Because in that platonic schema, right, this then sees God as being in a very platonic fashion on moving, right?
Pure act, separate.
And then when humans leave this life in this world, we escape from this becoming, right?
and this material world, enter into this sort of it.
now in which God dwells, this age in which God dwells. Right? And then this plays into the whole
idea of the beatific vision. And then the problem becomes, how you match that up with the bodily
resurrection. Hmm. Right? And so that becomes attention. I know I've commented on this on the show
before. You see this tension all the way through the third part of Thomas.
is Summa, which I know he didn't actually write himself.
It was compiled from his notes, but then maybe he had a resolution to the tension, but
there's still a tension there between the beatific vision and the bodily resurrection.
In the Western eschatology that develops, and it's really because of this platonic understanding
of St. Augustine, when it gets kind of followed out, right?
I don't see a lot of evidence that St. Augusta never followed it out that far.
but other people do, like Beethys, and Ansel.
But yeah, so then we have this idea of world without end,
and a similar idea to that world without end is expressed
in some of our orthodox liturgics,
when it talks about the day that has no end,
in some of our liturgics.
And that day...
there is being used in this sense of age, right?
That there will ultimately be an age that has no end.
And this is reflected in Revelation 21,
when St. John says that in the New Heavens
of the New Earth, there is no night.
Right? There's no night,
that means there's no end to the day.
Me and it goes on forever.
So, certain folks who are of a certain bent, maybe primarily identified by three initials.
Sorry. Like we said, of a certain bent, that was, I couldn't let that pass by.
They would very much like to argue.
that when the scriptures in the New Testament in Greek,
they point out that when it talks about,
for example, eternal death or eternal condemnation.
What we might colloquially call hell,
that what it actually says in Greek
is death or condemnation of the age.
Yeah, meaning of the Aew.
it has a big
beginning in an end. Right. And so they then point out, well, see, it's of the A-on, A-on's,
have beginnings in ends, days have beginnings in ends. Right. Yes. Usually they do. But
that doesn't mean that the concept of a day without an end, or an age without an end, is
inconceivable. And ultimately, where that kind of argument falls apart is that sometimes
literally in the same verse.
in the same sentence in the original, it will talk about life of the A-on, of the age,
which we translate as eternal life. Meaning that if condemnation has a beginning in an end,
then you have to translate that way about life as well, that there's...
Right. If condemnation is not eternal, then life can't be eternal either.
Right, right. If we can't conceive and whether they're used parallel.
It's kind of hard to argue when someone parallels eternal life and eternal
death that they mean different things by eternal.
Yeah.
It seems to me.
It doesn't stop some folks with three initials.
Some say.
Yes.
Someone somewhere has said.
Hey.
Yeah.
So that argument, that particular argument without waiting into the whole thing of
universalism. That particular argument just does not
work. Right. Right. It just does not work. So age, A-One does not imply a beginning and an end,
any more than day implies a beginning and an end. Yes, it's normal usage it does. It has a beginning
and end. Sure. But one can certainly conceive of and the scriptures do conceive of a day that has no
and an A on that has no end.
And a life that has no end.
Which means they can also, it is also possible for them to conceive of death or condemnation or what have you that has no end.
Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. So we will go further down that rabbit hole.
Is that's a whole can of worms. Maybe in a future episode that will make everyone mad.
Let's do it.
So there are a bunch of ages.
that are talked about in the scriptures.
Yeah, most of the first stage, which is when the somerals are made.
And then, sorry, wrong scriptures.
Yes, yeah, Bible, Rathika.
So, yeah, so there are these ages described in scripture.
Most of these are in the Old Testament period.
that are probably obvious. And they're described and the transitions are described. And these are
worth going through because they kind of exhibit different things that help us understand what we're
talking about, what we're talking about in age. And I think one thing that's really important to
note about this is that there's not a sense that they're all the same length. And they couldn't,
there's no way to make them all the same like you know.
looking at what's in the scripture.
Yeah.
So it's not a discrete unit of time.
Right.
Yeah.
So the first one is sort of creation,
sort of Genesis one.
Yeah, the period where God is actually making the world.
Right.
Before humans are created.
Yeah.
Right.
Before humans are created.
So there are no humans having human experience.
is an experiencing time the way humans experience time.
Right. This is an age which sort of has no beginning.
Now you say, well, wait, creation kind of had a beginning. It's like, well, sort of, except,
it's not like God was sitting around, I mean, sitting. God was alone.
goes the only thing that existed through this sort of infinite succession of moments of time.
And then one day, and then one moment decided, this is the moment where I'm going to make everything.
Yeah. I mean, you know, creation is not uncreated. It's not without beginning. But when we think of
beginnings, we tend to think of moments in time. Right. There wasn't time in any sense. Right.
So before God created time
just use the language before, right? But that's temporal language. Yeah, right. Like when I say,
so there's this moment of creation, right? The first moment of creation,
you and I could conceive of, well, there's, you know, there's a moment for that, right?
Right, there's a second before that.
Right.
Yeah, we can think that before that moment.
But there wasn't because moments were created at that moment.
So this is something we can't wrap our head around.
Yes.
Right. Because as we said before on the show,
this is a really important.
That's why we talk about not knowing what it's like to be a bat so much.
We have to keep this sort of epistemological point.
This point about how we know what we know.
And the fact that we can only see things from a certain human perspective, etc.
perspective, etc.
have to sort of always keep that in mind. It can be said that some things are true only from a certain point of
you. So when we focus, right, and we try to think, we try to imagine the moment of creation,
right, we are imagining ourselves being there watching it. Yeah, I mean, who is there writing it down
like, Oh, God is making right separating out the land from the, from the waters, write that down
somebody. Yeah.
and you were not there standing there watching it.
As God points out to Job most and faculty,
where were you when I was doing all this?
Yeah.
And it's, I wasn't.
Right, so there is no human observer to this.
So the concept of a first moment,
right, to even try to comprehend that,
we'd have to understand how God experiences time,
which again that's right off the table.
Right.
Completely off the table.
So, when we talk about this age, this age of creation being before the next age, which begins when humanity is created.
Right.
It's before in relation to the first humans.
It's referring to when they weren't.
But that is sort of an apophatic statement.
Yeah.
It's a statement that there was when Adam and Eve weren't.
And even Brian Williams wasn't.
But we cannot make a any kind of what we call cataphaq.
Any kind of literal statement about what that was or what it was like.
was like, right? Yeah.
And so that's why I told the Younger Creationists folks they didn't have to worry about the day age thing, right?
Because the day age thing fundamentally doesn't make sense.
But there's a period of time being denoted literally by the days of creation.
Right.
Period of time there's no humans.
So what does that even mean?
Yeah
So, but then the next age is paradise, right?
So, humans are created on day six as described in detail in Genesis two.
Humans get created, and this is the time in paradise before humanity is expelled from paradise.
The fact that there are now humans means that humans experience time in some way.
But it doesn't mean that they experienced it the same way we do now.
Right.
It's a very different world.
It's a different age.
It's a different world.
It's a different ordering of things in the creation.
It's the same creation, but the creation is ordered differently before.
Well, humanity is ordered differently before the expulsion for paradise as opposed to
after.
Right.
And that causes that's going to change how you
many experiences. And so that's why on one hand, we have in Genesis 2 and 3, a narrative
story of the creation of Adam out of the earth, naming of the animals, the creation of woman
from his side when he is split. And because like we can't tell a story in another way.
That's OK.
You're right.
Right. And even when we try, like even when we when we try to tell a non linear story,
what we're really doing is telling linear stories just in different bits and in different
orders. Yeah, out of order. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. We can't tell a non linear story. It's just
not a possible. Yeah. So we tell this story of the linear fashion, leading up to Tation,
Send the exposure for paradise because that's the way we can tell a story
a lot of times we fall into literally, this is literally a tree.
It's literally a piece of fruit, a pomegranate or something.
I don't know where the commercials getting that by the way for pomegranate juice.
And why why that would be a selling point either.
But right.
I'm like because because I mean that, you know, brings like all
there's going to Persephone and Haiti's things there going.
You two could rebel against God drink our juice.
Um, it was an apple though.
Like in the garden, it wasn't Apple because,
because Apple just used to mean fruit.
Well, plus it's stuck in my neck.
So, yeah, so we have this narrative,
and we tend to think of that in a very literal way.
And so then we'll read some of the church fathers
like St. Maximes who says that Adam fell
as he came into being and you're like,
well, wait, what?
Yeah, which makes no...
...literals like if you're...
That's not a statement that's bound by the linear linearity of the Genesis story. Right. Right
and but what
What St. Maximus is pointing to there as other fathers do in different ways like with the
Governments of skin that we've talked about before the difference in the human body
um
They're saying this is a different order of things and that carries with it a different way in which time is experienced
by humans. Right? So the fact that we have to describe something using words and syllables
and then recounting and reading aloud those words and syllables takes place over a period of time
does not necessarily mean that what we're describing was experienced over a period of time
in the same way. Right. Right. And think about I could, if I witnessed a car accident, right?
I could write you
A 1500 word super detailed description of the moment of impact, right?
It would still only be a moment of impact even though it might take you five minutes to read what I wrote.
Hmm. In the description. Right?
And that wouldn't mean that I was lying to you about.
All this stuff couldn't happen in one moment. Right?
I don't like this is, you know, so many minutes worth of material.
Right. So that's an example. That's just an analogy, right? That's not exactly what we're talking about. That's an analogy, right?
So then the expulsion from paradise is this transitional moment when we talk about the expulsion from paradise
That's really what we're talking about or we want to call it the fall or one of the falls
Right, we're talking about that transitional moment to now this
new age this new era this new world comes into being
which is the world.
outside of paradise leading up to the flood, right? The days of Noah, right? What's
recounted in the genealogies of Seth and Kane? So everything with the Nephilim,
everything with Lamyk and his wives and the spread of sin and all of those
things happening, right? This is a very differently ordered world, a
differently ordered humanity than uh
Paradise, very obviously, right?
There's a stark contrast between that age and the age which preceded it.
And then when we come to the flood,
the way the flood is very deliberately described. So the flood comes. This is our big transition event again.
And the flood is very deliberately described in terms of the uncreation of the world.
Yeah, right.
It's opposite order right of the, you know, there's death that comes in, you know, removing the
life and then the unstructuring happens. Right. Right. God separated the waters above from the waters
below and we read, you know, the springs come up and the water comes down from the firmament
that he put there to separate them. The dry land disappears back into the sea. Right. The
the world gets unmade, right? It goes lapses back into the
prime.
the word yokeos outside of the arc, right, in which the order of the world is preserved.
That's part of what's signified by the way by the fact that there are clean and unclean
animals on the arc.
Even though the Torah hasn't been given yet, right, that order is part of what's being
preserved there, not just the life, but also the order is preserved in the arc.
It's sort of a microcosm.
And then the world is recreated.
The water recedes from the dry land.
everything is separated again put back in order but it's a new order and so this new age begins after the flood
leading up to
to Abraham
Right meaning we're talking about what happens with the tower of Bable. Yeah
Then we have this other transitional moment right and then a big important one
right. Obviously that's going to be very important as we
as we go forward, the critical age in the Old Testament, because really Genesis, at all these
ages we've been discussing, Genesis is the prologue to the Torah, which begins in Exodus.
And so we have this very critical moment for the age that is going to predominate
in the well which is going to be basically the Hebrew Bible and predominate.
in the Christian Old Testament, which is the age
that's initiated by the giving of Torah at Sinai.
Because when the Torah is given at Sinai,
there is a fundamentally new order of things.
Israel now exists as a nation when the covenant is given,
when the Torah is received about Sinai.
Israel, as it comes into existence,
Now has a different relationship.
to the 70 nations and a role to play.
There is an order within Israel of the high priests, the priests, the people,
they have the concentric circles we've talked about of holiness that has to be maintained,
leading out into the nations.
Israel comes to serve as priests for the nations,
even as the priests that proper serve as the priests for Israel.
Israel, right? This order is established when
the Torah is given, that world that age then is initiated.
And that age ends when Judah goes into exile.
The temple is destroyed. Judah goes into exile.
and the return from exile then initiate
This new age, this post-exilic age, this post-exilic period, which Daniel refers to as the great tribulation.
Hmm.
So I know we're already upsetting.
This is going to be a rough night for our dispensationalist friends.
If there's still a thing.
I'm here for it.
Everybody got your clearance, lark, and illustrated manuals.
videos.
Right.
Okay.
your wall charts. So when Daniel talks about the great tribulation, he's talking about his own era
and the era to come in his prophetic visions that describe the coming of Alexander, the coming of
right, ultimately the coming of the Romans. And so this period, why is this a great tribulation?
more because this is a period when what's left of Israel, right? Judea, the tribe of Judea.
tribe of Benjamin, some Levites, right? That's sort of the remnant that's left.
Where in which they are not in control of their own land, they're under the oppression of foreign powers.
The abomination of desolation happens.
When you do get some kind of independent Judea under the Hasmonians,
They're throwing the Torah out left and right, right?
To the boy.
We have John here, canas being both King and High Priest at the same time.
They're playing fast and loose.
Right.
The scriptures.
A temple gets rebuilt, but then gets built upon by Herod.
Who's an itch-umian.
Also not a great guy, morally.
Right.
So from the perspective of all the way up until the time of Christ, right?
the time of Christ in Carnation.
time when he calls his disciples the time when he's preaching in Galilee and Jadiah.
Right, all the way up to that time period, this is what is considered the great tribulation.
And the idea is that this great tribulation is going to be ended when the Messiah comes
to deliver his people.
When the Messiah comes to deliver Israel, that's going to be the hinge point again that's
going to inaugurate the next stage.
Right. And until and from their perspective, all they had to do to prove that the Messiah
hadn't come yet was kind of look around.
Right.
Things are terrible.
This is still, if you talk to an Orthodox Jewish person today, right, this is their
biggest point of counter evidence when they're going to say that Jesus is not the Messiah
They'll say look around. Does this look like, uh, right to you?
right? We'll talk about that. Yes, from their perspective, right? They've continued to be right,
afflicted, oppressed, they're tiny, remnant, right? And so they've kind of maintained
right this view that predominated in in the first century. So the great tribulation
that's cited by the Messiah is not a future thing in Daniel. It's a current state of affairs in Daniel.
Yep.
It was what was going on at that time and we continue going on everything with Antioch is a bifinase
Everything with the Romans everything all the beasts in sequence
But Daniel describes that we talked about a little bit a little bit last time
And all of this is then looking forward to this messianic age
That's going to be inaugurated by the coming of the Messiah of the Christ
Yeah when he comes
and that's what we're going to talk about in the next half.
So we're going to go ahead and take our first
and we'll be right back with the Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Father Steven Cignari is back with more stories about Father Now.
and the Saint Alexander the whirling derbish parish.
They are only very nice and to you,
except the grain of wheat fall into the earth and die.
It abideseth by itself alone,
but if it die, it beareth much fruit.
Then they sang a hymn so sad about God's memory.
I don't believe there was a voice across the garden of graves
who went that day without weeping.
We ate so much after the Lord's...
a feast and a field on the hillside by a grave. I was at a banquet in God's garden of souls,
a headstone marking the name and location of each seed, and all his people as far as I could see
came alive with us that sunny morning on the hill. God's memory really is eternal.
So good, I said.
The priest said it was love made edible.
I wasn't exactly sure what, but something was happening.
Miriam said to me, this is church, Mr. Luther,
you should come and see.
This has been an excerpt from Bread from Home,
a collection of short stories written and read by
Father Steven C. Neary.
Now available at store.enginefaith.com.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymeck and Father Stephen D. Young
second of moment to take your calls on the
next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855 AFF.
radio. Thanks, boys of Steve. He promises he delivers immediately. Yes. So yeah, I mean to
be fair, you know, he does do that. Read live every single. So sometimes he gets a little
distracted or something. It's calling in from from Queens. Yeah. Yeah. Also, let me say
this. One of our previous metropolitan's at a certain point said, you know what? No more
Church's name St. George is St. Nicholas.
right? We got too many, right? We need to vary this up a little more. We need our churches
to be named after different saints. I'd like to issue a call to all of the Orthodox
bishops in the Americas. No more fathers Stephen. I was father Stephen before it was cool,
Now it's getting really confusing.
They're everywhere.
Yes.
Yeah.
It's not the...
can't our data guy name Steven you just gonna have to change his name change it yeah yeah I don't
know any father Barcinufi I right I'm about somebody out there is I mean there's a lot of
names there's lots of good saints names there's yeah there's there's plenty you know uh yeah yeah so
we're it's actually great we're we are live had someone ask me on youtube like are is this pre
recorded or you like multitasking or something but we are live
we actually have right now, we have live listeners from Japan, Australia, and Costa Rica,
at least, and I'm sure plenty from the good old US of A as well. So yeah, yeah, it's pretty,
oh yes, our Costa Rican listener says that their mission is name St. Nicholas.
He's apologizing for that.
Ask our Japanese list.
if he's excited about forbidden door.
Oh well, well, we'll see what he says to that.
But yes, so meanwhile, we actually do have a caller here.
So Aaron, we have you calling and are you on the line?
Yes, yes I am.
Can you guys hear me?
We hear you.
Welcome Aaron's the Lord of Spirits podcast.
What are you thinking about?
Well, I'm surprised I got in first, but...
You're in.
You made it, man.
Yeah.
So I have been thinking a lot lately about, I really like moving metropolis and it's like
19th century leading into the 20th century just on the topic of kind of like millennium
But that movie had the conceptualization of MOLIC as the soon-
of industrial society like eating people.
And I always, I mean, lately I was thinking about how similar
in this way that kind of,
Mollick as the old idea,
and then Manon as the idea of kind of like money
over everything agreed, this kind of spiritual pollutant.
And so I was thinking about how these two kind of come together
Uh...
And I know often the parking list those answers that are these things to be thought of as
symbols of being or entities unto themselves. Are they the same? Are they different modalities
of the evil of this century now, or are they just the same thing?
Yeah.
Well, there are a lot of demons around.
Fewer than there were.
Thanks be to God. Fewer than there were.
But yeah, there's a lot of demons around.
So, as we've said before, they're lying chaos monsters.
So, how can we tell if there's one particular spirit
that's doing one thing and then another one that's doing something else?
That's super hard to tell, right?
But
And even like so they've got mollock, mollock, mollack,
mamen, et cetera, that are mentioned specifically in scripture as names,
but those could represent a bunch of different spirits potentially.
We just kind of don't know.
You know, they don't stand up and like show us their IDs.
Yeah.
You know, believe them if they did.
Exactly.
Because they're lying chaos monsters.
You know, so I don't-
of father you got anything you wanted to add or subtract or whatever.
First of all, kudos for liking German expressionist cinema.
My favorite genre film.
Yeah.
You've seen M.I. assume.
Of course.
Yeah, great movie.
Anyway, we won't turn this into a movie podcast.
But so yeah, so I think it's incontrovertible.
If we're trying to determine, right, so sort of what are, right, what are the gods that
are societies inadvertently worshipping?
Right, and I agree with you that that movie is kind of insightful in that respect.
Yeah.
that there is this worship of profit and success and indulgence.
right, which is basically what we're talking about when we're talking about Maman.
And it is a kind of worship that demands the sacrifice of children and family
right and social bonds right it is sort of you know everything solid melt into air right it's it's
It's just this corrosive right aspect.
And so I mean, I think there is there is definitely something there, right?
As Father Andrew said, right, we can't like, you know, demons don't wear a name tag
that says like hello.
My name is, you know, man, man, right.
My name is my name is Bullock.
I'm the exact same guy who was in that idol in the Valley of him.
That's the one.
Right.
You know, but.
That is definitely the thread.
Right, that has been behind a lot of
the drive of our society.
And this has, I mean, this has a concrete thing, right?
In the United States, Roby Wiggits overturned
and immediately Amazon steps up and says,
oh, we'll pay for abortions.
We don't want people taking maternity leave.
We want to keep them at work.
Right? And you look at the way, you know, at a certain point in the mid-20th century,
women get told, hey, we're going to empower you. We're going to liberate you from being, you know,
chained to the oven. You know, you're going to be able to go out and have a career. And then
women entering the workforce creates an abundance of labor, drives down wages. And now everybody needs to
to have a two in.
household go figure. And instead of being free, now everybody's enslaved to have to work just to try to support themselves where they used to be able to be supported on one income.
And what that's done to the family. And now in states all over the US at least they're trying to repeal child labor laws and lower the working age.
So soon it's going to be all the teenage kids are going to have to go out and get jobs to support their families too.
And so when I talk about the corrosion of social bonds.
I'm not just talking about a theoretical level, right?
I'm talking about it at a really practical level,
that our worship of this prosperity and success and indulgence
and a lifestyle is destroying our social bonds
and destroying our humanity.
And if that's not demonic, I sort of don't know what is.
So all that is to say yes.
It's not depressing.
it all. No, not great. Not great. Yeah.
Good to know. Yeah, I gave you the long answer first of the
short answer this time. Yeah.
Gary did up a little bit. I will just say I am eagerly
awaiting for Bitten Door. Okay. Good. All right. Good. Yeah.
Match you're most excited about. Um, I think Okata Danielson.
That's that's all. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. He said anything else I
I would have questioned you.
It's right.
Yeah, I know that's yeah,
a match of a lifetime.
Yeah, seriously.
Okay.
All right. Well, thank you very much for calling in Aaron.
I just got notes that we have.
We have a list of from Sweden right now, which like that's dedication
because it's two in the morning and sweet.
Yes.
You know, the people out in the Pacific Rim, it's just it's like eight
or nine nine a.m. 10 a.m. depending on where they are.
We have an Alaska listener as well.
so it's still I think afternoon there.
But good for you, Bjorn Bjorn.
Yes, from Sweden.
That is the most Swedish name ever.
Yeah, that is pretty Swedish.
That's a good.
I won't mention his last name because I don't want to out him.
Yeah, maybe so.
His last name is very Swedish as well.
So an actual sweet.
Is that Bjornson, I hope?
No, no, Bjorn Bjornson would be a little too stereotypical.
But amazing.
Yeah.
OK, we do have a couple more callers.
So next is Phil.
So, feel welcome to Lord of Spirits Park.
Yes.
Hey, fathers.
I called back during the World of the Q&A sessions.
I'm a fellow from South Carolina.
Welcome back.
Thank you for talking to me.
And I had a question about, you mentioned the word A on.
Am I pronouncing that right?
Sure.
Roughly, give or take.
Is that related to the word E on as a period of time?
Oh good, I feel a logical...
question. I got to do etymology. That's right. I don't have my jingle ready to roll. Oh, well.
I don't, man, I feel lost. Yeah. So, Ion, yeah, Ion is, um, it gets spelled in different ways in
English like, Ion, like, E-O-N, but, but also A-E-O-N, which betrays its roots, right? So, in English,
we get it from Latin and Latin just browse it straight from Greek.
A on, right? So it's directly descended from the Greek term that we're talking about earlier.
And ultimately it comes from a proto-indoe-European route that seems to have meant
something like lifetime or a long time, but also even used to mean things like eternity as well.
So yeah, so there's another related Greek word which is i.e. spelled alpha epsilon yota,
which means always.
And we have, there's a good old archaic English word, I, A, Y, E,
which isn't really used very much anymore, except to mean yes,
but like in a naval context, like I, I, sir, right?
But or in the old comic books that came with masters
of the universe figures.
Oh, that's true.
That's true, but yeah, it also meant, you know, forever, right?
So yeah, it is directly directly.
descended from the English word,
Ion is directly descended from the Greek Aeon.
Oh, it really is kind of the same word.
Well, yeah, I mean, I think that the way that it is used
in English even now, yes.
I mean, words do change over the centuries,
but I think that English Ion, that's essentially what we
mean by it, is a period, a time on age.
Like I might say, well, I've been doing this for Ion's,
which is hyperbole.
I don't mean I've been doing
it for thousands of years, but a long period of time or it's been an eons since we were
speaking middle English, whatever.
Oh, okay.
Okay.
So yeah, I mean, we do have...
Yeah.
That answers that question.
I appreciate it.
And I listened to myself the last time I called and I realized I'd laid on my accent a
little too hard and I sounded like Paul Corn.
leg horn so I was trying to tone that down to that. By no means. So I appreciate y'all
the show and this is a good show. Thank God. Thank God. I'm always happy to hear from
southerners. I lived in the south for a good long time and I love the south. Love it. So
I'll go eat some grits for you. Oh thank you. Crack open a cheer wine for him. See I'm surprised
it didn't say yeah like grits really right if you're like a
It's certain parts of South. That's a multi-Solavic word like grids
Grids, yeah, I don't know how you say it in South Carolina though, but I've heard grids like Alabama's will say that I think
Yeah, yeah, all right. Well, thanks
A single grit yeah
Yeah, you don't eat it's real. Yeah, it's not a thing. How would you do that with tweezers?
Anyway, thanks very much for calling this video.
We're gonna take one more client before we continue on and we've got was kind of on the line
I gotta be honest that's kind of hoping for a follow-up about a on flux. Oh
Well, yeah
So Brett are you are you there Brett?
Yeah, father's on here. All right welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast. What is this person? I know
Is it the person you know bothers Steven? Yes? Yeah?
Is it that Brad or it's that Brad but but
Yeah, you've met him, I think.
Father, I don't know.
We did meet at the Clarke or Treat about a year ago now.
Okay.
Yes.
At least this time.
Go ahead.
My true question is getting Father Stevens opinion on something in the 41st millennium, since we're talking about millenniums today, but I'll refrain from asking that.
And focus on this current millennium.
So in the show before we have you have related roles.
to America and we just finished mentioning about the division's end annual and
that relating to the fall of Roman the fall of that age.
It would have since a role with an icon of that age, we could say maybe America is an
icon of this current age.
Would the fall of America then bring the downfall of this current age and the
welcoming of the new one?
Wow, how important is America?
What do you think Father Steven?
very so no.
Um, there were now that takes a people off.
There's no one people freak it out about that.
No one ever asks about the place of Latvia in biblical prophecy.
Yes, exactly.
Yeah.
But the Latvians not even I don't know honestly.
I didn't want to throw out Lithuania because I didn't want to be epicentric because I know the
Serbs think they were the first created humans.
That's from you.
All the day that they're descended.
The Garden of Eden is somebody that's Adam and Eve were Serbs.
But yeah, so the answer that's new in that.
So it's correct that America is sort of
an instantiation of the beast, right?
A world empire in the present day, right?
In our present day.
But your core question.
is really about how the lifespan of the United States of America relates to the age as a whole.
And within the age in which we're currently living, which we're going to be talking about more here in the second half,
America is even like the US as an existing thing is a relative newcomer.
You had the British Empire before that.
before that, you had other colonial empires, right, which were also
of that same sort of reality, right?
In fact, America really became an imperial kind of state
after World War II when the British Empire finally
keeled over after its long death rose.
So I don't think it has that kind of pivotal role.
Now, as we were talking about with the Antichrist
the Antichrist in the last episode.
I mean, eventually there will be a last one.
Right.
Eventually there will be some embodiment, some kind of world empire embodiment, right, of
Leviathan of the beast when when Christ returns, right, when when Christ glorious peering
happens.
But we have no necessary reason to believe that that's still going to be the US.
the US could see.
to exist, the US could just cease to be an empire the way Britain did. And, right,
and things could roll on without us. Yeah. For folks, all those folks who are listening
who aren't in America, I'm sure they think America is weird. In this respect that we think
were that important. In fact, I have seen photos of a textbook used in German schools,
they use American Patriot
is a patriotism is an example of government indoctrination and propagandists. The Germans.
Wow. That's wow. But yeah, we think we're very exceptional and that, you know, just like in
St. Augustine's day, right? The end of that world order was the end of the world period to them.
And he's kind of like, we need to hear the same message in the United States. The end of the
of the data.
state is not the end of the world necessarily.
Might be the end of our world.
We might get onto the, you know, follow
civilization's podcast.
Yes, yeah.
Yeah.
But yeah.
All right.
Well, thank you very much for calling,
Brett.
I'll thank you for the answers,
fathers.
Yep.
All right.
The Messianic Age.
That's what we're doing on the second half of the.
Yes.
of this year podcast.
Not for an age, but for all time.
Yeah.
So, yeah, so the age to which during the great tribulation, as we said, the people at the
time of Christ were looking forward to is the Messianic age, right?
age of the Christ of the Messiah.
So they...
when they talk about it in Jewish literature,
when they talk about the transition,
they tend to compare it to previous transitional events.
So they're looking forward to this transition.
Like this event is gonna happen,
the coming of the Messiah,
that is gonna transition us into this Messianic age.
And so as a way to understand it before the fact,
they look to previous transitions. So for example, when you read the inachic
literature, the inachic literature is all using the days of Noah and the
approaching of the flood to talk about the coming of the Messiah and the coming of
the day of the Lord, right, the day of Yahweh by way of comparison, right? So
Um...
This is narrated in Firsteanek to a lesser degree in Secondeanek, where the Firsteanek
repeatedly, because Firsteanek is this composite of several different texts, but we have, there's
a book of Noah that's incorporated into Firsteanek, right?
This sort of directly dealing with this, the birth of Noah, and Noah being portrayed
as this messianic figure through whom the world is going to be saved, and they're going
transition into this new age free from all the sin and wickedness of that age.
Is that the one where he's born glowing and talking?
Yes.
Yeah.
So, yeah.
Sorry.
So, but, and so we get this idea that, right, and they portray Noah's day, we don't see
actually described in the text of Scripture that there's this sort of direct persecution
of Noah in his family.
Right.
that sort of the psorias people are out to destroy him, but that does become a factor in the
anachic literature because, again, its comparison is being made to the great tribulation and the
things that are happening to Judea during this period from which those going to deliver them.
And so they're looking at, okay, let's look at that transition and use that as a window into this
transition that we're hoping and praying for as we go through this period of tribulation.
So that's the inoculate.
that's pretty much extra biblical, but bits of that do come into the New Testament.
Right? As in the days of Noah, right, when people are being married and given in marriage,
before the flood came, so will it be in the day of the Son of the Man when Christ returns?
Right? So you see some of those themes get picked up and used in a slightly different way in the New Testament.
Once Jesus and Nazareth has come as the Messiah.
the most well-known way, though in which this is described prospectively, right? Looking forward
from the Old Testament is as a new covenant, that a new covenant is going to come. And when
it's talked about in terms of a new covenant, we have to remember that what's being talked about
here, what's really happening here is that this transitional event that's going to lead into the
the Messianic Age is being...
compared to the giving of the covenant of Mount Sinai,
which was that transitional moment
into the age of the Hebrew scriptures,
into the age of most of the Old Testament.
And so this is, again, a comparison being made
to a transitional event, right?
In this case, not the flood,
but the giving of the Torah at Sinai, right?
And the ordering of the world
and of Israel's poor
place in it that happened at that time.
And probably the most famous Hebrew Bible slash
Christian Old Testament text regarding the new covenant
comes from Jeremiah 31.
Yeah.
So this is verses 31 through 34.
Behold, the days are coming to Clair's the Lord
when I will make a new covenant with the House of Israel
and the House of Judah.
Not like the covenant that I made with their fathers
on the day when I took them but
hand to bring them out of the land of Egypt, my covenant that they broke, though I was
their husband, declares the Lord.
For this is the covenant that I will make with the house of Israel after those days,
declares the Lord.
I will put my law within them, and I will write it on their hearts, and I will be their
God, and they shall be my people.
And no longer shall each one teach his neighbor and just each his brother saying, no, the
Lord, for they shall all know me from the least of them to the greatest declares the Lord.
I will forgive their iniquity and I will remember their sin no more.
It's interesting to me like one of the things I notice about this is that the new covenant
is described as being with Israel.
Yes.
Not with some other entity.
Right.
With Israel and Judah.
Yeah, right.
Right.
So it's explicitly talking about here the northern kingdom of Israel, which has ceased to
exist.
Yeah.
Because it's been scattered out amongst the nations.
Yeah, and so this is a promise of reuniting, right?
Because then he switches to first he says you come in with the house of Israel and the house of Judah, and then he says this is the covenant I'll make with the house of Israel because once they're reunited there Israel.
Yeah.
Right.
And so the new test of authors, especially St. Paul in Romans 9 through 11 is what Romans 9 through 11 is actually about, especially 10 and 11, is going to see.
Gentiles being grafted in as this restoration of the Northern Kingdom.
But yes, in terms of our poor dispensationalist friends who are going to be battered over the course of the evening.
The New Covenant is not with a new group, right?
This is not I will this is the new covenant I will make with this new group of Gentiles that I'm going to call the church.
Yeah, and then so
A couple more passages that talk about the new covenant are in Ezekiel.
Yes, so the first one is Ezekiel 11 verses 19 and 20.
And I will give them one heart and a new spirit I will put within them.
I will remove the heart of stone from their flesh and give them a heart of flesh.
That they may walk in my statutes and keep my rules and obey them.
And they shall be my people and I will be their God.
There's that covenant language.
again, they should be my people and I will be their God.
Yeah.
And the other one is a little later in in Ezekiel.
And it repeats some of the same kind of language.
So this is Ezekiel 36 versus 26 through 32.
And I will give you a new heart and a new spirit I will put within you.
And I will remove the heart of stone from your flesh and give you a heart of flesh.
And I will put my spirit within you and cause you to walk in my
statutes and be careful to obey my rules. You shall dwell in the land that I gave to your
fathers, and you shall be my people, and I will be your God. And I will deliver you from
all your uncleanesses, and I will summon the grain and make it abundant and lay no famine
upon you. I will make the fruit of the tree and the increase of the field abundant that
you may never again suffer the disgrace of famine among the nations. Then you will remember
your evil ways and your deeds that were not good, and you will loath yourselves for your
in your abominations.
It is not for your sake.
that I will act to declare as the Lord God.
Let that be known to you.
Be ashamed and confounded for your ways,
O house of Israel.
So that last little bit, right,
is kind of countering what would become
the predominant at the time of Christ's fairer say of view,
which the fairer say of view of that time
makes pretty good sense, right?
On a logical level, they said,
Look, sinning, goddess, in-
this mess, right? Violating the Torah. I got to say this mess. So if we could all just obey
Torah, then God will respond by sending the Messiah. Yeah, but he says it's not for your sake that I
will act. Right. Right. Right. And so this runs sort of counter to that. Right. Yeah. So, but it's
important to keep in mind what is reflected here, right? Because these are all prophetic, not in the
the sense of being uttered.
by a prophet, but also in the sense in which we sometimes commonly use it of talking about
the future.
Right?
This is God talking about what He will do when the new covenant comes.
What He will do when the new covenant comes.
And He is not characterizing this as abolishing the old covenant.
Right?
He is not talking about this as abolishing the Torah.
Quite the opposite.
it. Yeah, it's that it becomes internal now. It's going to be in your heart because the
spirit is going to be within you so that you can live out the Torah. Right. The spirit is going to
empower. Right. The Holy Spirit, the Spirit of God, capital S spirit is going to come into you and
empower you to keep it. That's how it's going to be different than last time. It's not going to be
different than last time because last time you had all these rules and now we don't worry about rules
anymore. Yeah.
Now, we just go, hey man, it's all good.
It's cool, right?
It's different in that before, right, they failed to keep the Torah because they couldn't
do it under their power.
And now the Holy Spirit is going to be placed in them.
They're going to receive a heart of flesh and the Holy Spirit in them is going to empower
them to keep what St. Paul will call the righteous requirements of the law.
We'll be kept in them, right?
So there is no, in the new covenant, there is no lowering of the bar.
Right?
If anything, there is a raising.
Yes, there is no scrapping of the, there is an empowering, right, to do.
Right.
That's what's going on here.
And so when St. Paul talks about the letter in the spirit or to talks about the law and the spirit,
He's not contrasting these in the sense of saying law-bad spirit good.
He's saying, the letter, trying to keep the Torah historically, Israel failed, but now
walking by the Spirit, now we can keep the righteous requirements of the Torah that
God has for us, empowered by the Holy Spirit.
This is what he's getting at when the inhalation delays out.
the fruit of the Spirit, right? Love, joy, peace, patience, kindness, goodness, faithfulness,
gentleness, self-control, against these things there is no law, right? That by the Holy Spirit
dwelling within us and producing those fruit, it has the effect of us keeping the Torah, right?
If we love our brother, we're not going to harm him or to evil-tam, right?
We're not good.
be envious and jealous, right? We're at peace, right? We're not going to be. It's right, right? And so
this is the hoist we're powering us to go further, right? And this isn't just something Father
Stephen came up with to argue against Protestantism or to hang out with his cool Paul with
and Judaism buds. Uh, it's scholarly circles. This is how St. John Chrysostom reads Romans.
If you want the key element, you can go and read them, his homilies on Romans.
The key element of his interpretation all the way through that St. John, Chrysostom, points
out is that the Holy Spirit empowers us to keep the law, the righteous requirements
of the law.
As Christians, right?
Over and over again, he says that as he's interpreting and reading St. Paul.
I know we're not.
post to quote, protistics on this show. There's like a rule that we'd never do it. But oops,
I just did. Take that Twitter. Yeah. So, so, right. Now, of course, within this concept
of the new covenant, right?
There comes to be.
Um, let the shifting light at the end of your tunnel is just a freight train coming
away. No, that's another. Um, there comes to be a whole school of theology called
covenant theology, right? And if you're, you're like me and you grew up in reformed circles
and you use the word covenant online as an orthodox priest, you will be accused of have,
of being still secretly a Calvinist. Let me just tell you for personal experience, you
can't even use this.
word coveted because they could say, oh, you hold to coveted theology. It's in the Bible.
The word is in the Bible. Bereak people. You're cheeky. Anyway.
So what coveted theology is, is, and this is particularly popular in
English reform circles, more than continental reform circles. So there's some of it in continental
performance circles. But it's primarily in...
English-war meaning Presbyterian circles.
Covenant theology takes this paradigm of the age inaugurated by the giving of the covenant
at Sinai and then the Messianic Age is inaugurated by the giving of the new covenant and then
takes that covenant framework and uses it as the lens through which the whole scriptures
red.
Doing that in some cases provides helpful insights and in some cases is reductionist.
Meaning it causes you to miss things, right?
Because when all you've got to hammer everything starts looking like a nail.
You start trying to hammer screws in.
And you start missing things because you've got this very narrow grid that you're looking at things through.
In actual reformed covenant theology
It kind of gets out of control and goes to the point where you're talking about
intra-trinitarian covenants in eternity. Right, like a covenant between God the Father and God the Son.
Yeah. In eternity. That's right. Like I just it just blows my mind to even conceptualize that.
Yes. Yes. And even when I was
studying this stuff in a Reformed Seminary.
at one point in my life, I kind of thought the idea that God the father and eternity passed
issued God the son, a hitite suzerain T. Treaty was a little weird. And maybe again, a little
reductionist, right? You find something and this is something to which all scholars are prone.
Sure. Right. And to which I am probably prone. I probably have blind spots related to this
that I'm not aware of, where you find a good insight.
And it's really helpful for understanding certain things and you latch on to it, but then
you just try and use it like a skeleton key everywhere.
And so some of your results are often weird, right?
So some of the places where I'm wrong, I'm sure that's why.
So I'm not criticizing, you know, I am admittedly prone to the same criticism, I'm sure in various
ways.
But that's ultimately where covenant theology kind of goes sideways.
It's helpful as it is.
in some cases, right, in some instances for understanding parts of Scripture.
Dispensationalism proper is a sort of subspecies of covenant theology.
So the word dispensation is being used in place of the word covenant.
Thomas Darby, who's credited with sort of inventing dispensationalism,
was a Presbyterian.
There was coming out of a cup
and theology milieu. And so part of what separates then
dispensationalism as such is a question of the level of continuity and
discontent between the covenants or the dispensations.
Yeah.
raised with this stuff. It was taught in most of the churches that I grew up in. I mean,
at least the way that it filtered down to, you know, me as a kid, I guess. But I think this
is still generally true with dispensationalists. The key parts is the idea that God sets up this
dispensation of the Old Testament, and this is how you get salvation is by obeying the law.
And then, and, you know, that dispensation.
is still in play for Jews now. They can obey all the law and they'll be saved.
Right? And then there's another dispensation which is the dispensation of grace.
And that's how Christians get saved. You become a Christian by doing that. And so there's a side,
there's this, it's not just the idea that there's different eras, but like there's different
deals that you can attain salvation through. You can either go obey all the law or you can
and accept Jesus into your heart.
and acknowledge them as the Lord of your life.
And I mean, there's a lot of people that still,
like those say things like,
Judaism is completely valid.
And if you really do that,
then you can be saved by Christianity also.
And so there's this kind of side by side,
two different paths that you can potentially take.
And that's the way that it kind of plays out
for a lot of people.
Of course, I mean, it's not only has big theological
implications, but it has geopolitical implications
we don't have any of those
stuff that we don't need to get into. But I mean, dispensational things really Lincoln's
fault. Yeah. Yeah. It, um, but I'm not just saying any more than that. See, it's always
some Yankee. Um, but yeah, it's not just some weird little corner of, of, of, uh, Protestantism.
It's as a huge impact actually on the way a lot of people think. Yeah. Yeah. And so there's
this.
fundamental discontinuity between the dispensations rather than continuity. Right? They are fundamentally
different. They're separate. There's no overlap. The Venn diagram is two circles next to
each other, right? Of the of the dispensations. So how is how is a dispensation or even a covenant
really? Right? In the way it's talked about in covenant theology. How is that different than what
what we're talking about when we talk about these.
different ages. Right? So when we talk about different ages, we're talking about different
metaphysical realities, even though metaphysical reality is kind of redundant. We're talking
about different structuring of the cosmos, right? Different fundamental structuring of the
human person, the world in which humans live.
and therefore the relationship between and the experience of the world that those humans have.
There's a metaphysical element. There's a real element to it that is transformed in these
transitions from age to age. This is, by the way, since we're in this new COVID
context, every once in a while I get asked the question, especially around pedicosts, we're
talking about pedicosts. Well now, everyone has the Holy Spirit. The Holy COVID is only
of these certain selects.
people had the Holy Spirit. We've talked about this on the show before, right? Well, how's it different?
Right? Like, like, function, does it, does it feel different? Right? I guess this question did,
did humans, the old coveted who didn't have the Holy Spirit within them feel differently than I feel?
Now, right? How would you know how to exactly? Yeah, exactly because it could be because
to an extent humans were different than humans were ordered differently then.
Right, this transition is take place. This is a different world in a sense. Not a materially
different world. Like materially that world ceased to exist. It was destroyed and a new one was
created X-Me-Holo, right? Like, the matter. But it's been reordered.
Yeah, and human consciousness I would say has a different character.
I mean, at least like, yeah, that's evident even like that's evident even now between cultures.
Right. I mean, you know, now we have more in common now with each other than we would with an
ancient person, but there is different a different sense. Like, I learned recently, and I'm sure I'm
getting this wrong on some level, but I learned recently that Korean, the Korean language, like, has
different sets of verbs and vocabulary that you use depending on the formality of the relationship
of the other person you're talking to.
English has nothing like this,
except for there's maybe a sense of
there's certain words you shouldn't say
in certain situations.
Like they're bad, it's a fanity.
But you're not using fundamentally different grammar
and nouns to talk to your superior versus your kid.
And so that's a very different way of thinking.
And that's just between cultures that exist now.
Yeah.
You know?
And so we're talking about a whole different
Meritism.
structure. Whereas as Father Andrew was kind of indicating the idea of a
dispensation or even of a covenant is it's sort of a deal, right? Yeah. It's a
set of conditions, right, leading to the reward of salvation, right? Meaning it's
It's not metaphysical.
Right.
The difference is not...
how a human is ordered or the nature of the human person or the nature of the world around them.
The difference is just, while this person living at this time needs to do this to inherit eternal life,
and this other person living at this other time needs to do that.
Yeah, it's like the laws have changed.
Like getting a green card in 2023 to the US is different than getting it in 1940.
Right.
And so that means...
transitions, right? The transitions between ages, as we've talked about, are these transformations?
Sometimes kind of apocalyptic in the more common modern sense of the word,
transitions, right, from one to one world, one ordering of things to another,
right? Whereas, in covenant theology or dispensationalism, it's sort of,
Literally what covered the
the issuing of a new document, the cutting of a new covenant.
Yeah, right.
Right, here are the new terms of the, right.
And so this is not coincidental, right?
This is sort of built into the different ways in which
classically Protestantism, right, especially reformed Protestantism
and orthodoxy, sea salvation.
Yeah.
Because I mean, the big question in Protestant
So theology is what is my relationship to God?
And it's broken so I need to fix it.
Right.
You know, which is just another way of kind of
working through the satisfaction theology
that was already present there when the reformation
came out of the scene.
Right.
It's that relate, it's a relational,
it's not a metaphysical, it's not an ontological
Yeah, transformation.
Yeah, which is why you can even get like this like you know Luther's snow covered dung thing right like you're still garbage
But God sees you differently now, you know is I mean that's that's that's
I said it nicer than he did
Right
Yeah, and this is and this is across the board right we're talking about transformation. We're talking about theosis
You know what we were talking about before st. John Crassostum
Christ kept
the law so you don't have to because you couldn't anyway versus the Holy Spirit keeps it in you.
Those are two very different positions.
Right. And two very different ways of reading St. Paul.
Yeah. Right. In Romans in particular. Yeah. And so that plays out in our understanding of
of even history in this sense.
right, and of ages, right, that same basic differences reflected.
So the new covenant is one way, right, that that the Messianic age gets talked about.
Another way it gets talked about is in terms of this being the age of the Holy Spirit,
as we were just kind of mentioning.
This is the age in which the Holy Spirit is going to be poured forth on all flesh.
And of course, it's one of the Locust Classicas for that.
is in Joel chapter 2.
Yeah, yeah.
So Joel 2 verses 28 through 32.
And it shall come to pass afterward
that I will pour out my spirit on all flesh.
Your sons and your daughters shall prophesy
your old, mental dream dreams,
and your young, mental, sevisions.
Even on the male and female servants in those days
I will pour out my spirit.
And I will show wonders in the heavens
and on the earth, blood and fire and columns of smoke.
The sun shall be turned to darkness in the moon
to blood before the great and
day of the Lord comes. And it shall come to pass that everyone who calls on the name of the Lord shall be saved.
For in Mount Zion and in Jerusalem there shall be those who escape, as the Lord has said, and among the survivors shall be those whom the Lord calls.
So, obviously this gets quoted at Pentecost and Act as being fulfilled at that time.
You can see how...
We read a couple of excerverses there in Joel how the pouring out of the Spirit on all flesh is tied to this day of the Lord
imagery
Right the day of Yahweh imagery
With the sun turning to darkness in the moon to blood
St. Luke of course applies that imagery to Christ crucifixion
And then of course at the beginning at the end of his gospel and at the beginning of Acts
We get the coming of the Holy Spirit at Pentecost.
It's important to remember that this is Pentecost, right? Pentecost is the feast
at which the giving of the Torah at Sinai is commemorated and the people recommit themselves
to keeping the Torah.
So this imagery of the age of the spirit is not sort of at all.
with the new covenant imagery, right? The covenant at Sinai, right? This is looking at the same
reality of the Messianic Age from another angle. Yeah, right. And of course those quotes that
you've come and talked about the Spirit coming and dwelling within people too. And so we would be
we would be remiss in talking about the Millennium and in talking about the age of the Spirit,
to not talk about walking day-fuel.
Who everybody knows about walking to Fuora?
Well, I thought folks did, but you didn't.
I did not.
I realized I had heard of him, but I was like, I don't remember who this guy is.
Yeah.
Yeah, he's late 12, very, very early 13th.
Like his dates are 1135 to 1202.
And with the name of like that, of course, he is Italian.
Um
But yeah, so what's his deal?
He's got a walk.
Just walking is a form of of Joaquin.
Yeah, exactly.
Right. Right.
That's the same. He's named after.
So yeah, walking day,
Fury had a theory.
And it was a theory about the ages of the world,
about the how to periodize the history of the world.
world.
future from his perspective at the very dawn of the 13th century. So he divided the whole history
of the earth of the world into three ages based on the Holy Trinity. So this seems like
an interesting thing to do. We like having things in threes, cherries, I think it's good,
it's Trinitarian.
and parts of this may even sound kind of intuitive, right?
So he says, so the Old Testament period
from the creation of the world, right,
through the whole, right, Christian Old Testament,
this is the age of the Father.
Okay, I mean, there's people these days that kind of
yeah, that's why I say,
I may even see kind of intuitive to people.
You might see why he did this.
Now it is a little problematic when we start going into details
as we have on the show before to just say,
Oh the God of the Old Testament is the...
father. Right. Right. Because some shows up and talks to God. Yeah. But, but okay. Right.
Sure. Right. And then beginning with the incarnation, right up until the year AD 1260. 1260, which
happened after his death, 58 years after a fucking defuora dies. Right. He says, this is the
the age of the sun.
Christ is born.
right? Lives, dies is resurrected, ascends into heaven, right? And the gospel goes out to all the nations of the world, right?
And this period ends in the medieval period in 1260, right?
In the year 1260.
It's predicted will end in 1260. And now here's where things get a little interesting.
Because if you leave it in 1260, this will begin
the third and final age, the age of the Holy Spirit, which is going to be this
sort of utopian age where and it's going to sort of be the end product of the
gospel having gone out to all the nations. So just in my description of that,
Right, some of our listeners...
who are familiar with more modern post-millennialism,
may see shades of that here, you're not wrong.
Right.
Walking day for your thoughts,
thoughts sets a bunch of these sort of
theological thought trends in the West in particular.
Yeah.
That then take these little currents
and branch out in different ways.
I at one point had a
professor who swore that one of those rivulets down at the end of one of those branches was George
William Frederick Aigle, but we definitely won't go there right now. I mean, one thing that's kind
of amazing to me, like if this utopian, I mean, I would hope it would be obvious that the fury is
wrong about these things. If only because 80 some years after his utopian age commences, the black
Death sweeps through your open-
feels a third of the population.
Right, but, but, but, not so.
You've got to remember what history has shown us, right?
Humans have a great ability to look at something like this
and say, this guy had great ideas
he just got the dates wrong.
Right, I mean, my favorite being, my personal favorite
being what was called the Great Disappointment
in the 19th century, where, you know, Jesus was supposed
to come back in what was in 1844, in October of 1844,
And he doesn't.
They're like, oh, actually he did, but it was a thing that happened in heaven.
Yeah, it was the thing that happened in heaven.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So that's sort of what happens here with Joaquin.
Sure.
Joaquin himself is never condemned as a heretic, but just about everybody who picks up where
he left off with his ideas does end up getting condemned.
Yeah, so there's some interesting groups. There's the
Amal Rishians, AMAL, RIC, IANS, the Ducinians, and then I, this is my favorite, the brethren
of the free spirit.
Yes, which all of which work at the end of my Rome, right?
Yeah, because there's a deep one.
There's shades of this, right?
And post-millennialism in, even in things like utopian socialism and there's even shades
of it, I think.
I think you have a better case for this big and influence.
on marks and some of the early Marxists
that on Hegel himself.
This idea that although they take it in a material way,
this idea of there being humanity growing toward this utopian end,
that all of this is going to resolve itself
into utopia being brought about by the spread of the gospel.
As an interesting side note, apparently there are some
Apparently there are some...
I'm not a scholar of this stuff, but there are some who say that he influenced Dante.
So, kind of an interesting read, I guess.
Yeah, so he's a fascinating guy, right, and his thought is fascinating.
But there don't seem to be a lot of really strong cohesive tethers of it to say scripture
or preceding Christian tradition, right?
Yeah, it's just sort of a neat model in a certain way.
But what is he basing it all on?
Yeah, yeah. And especially once, so I mean if you really dig into it, there's a reason why he picked 1260. He was doing working with numbers in the Bible.
Yeah, regarding ages. And even though it's very easy for us to say, hey, these are cool ideas. He just got the numbers wrong.
Eventually, if the numbers are wrong, the whole theory falls apart, right? Because some of it is based on the math.
Yep, right
So you can only kind of do that to a
limited degree. Right. Unless, again, unless you take it in a purely materialist way, and then it's
like, well, yeah, they don't have to be connected to the Bible or anything. It's just this is a good
idea. Let's bring about a utopia, right, on earth, through education or revolution or whatever.
Right. That has to work this time, either historically. Yeah.
So yeah, so and
That's, I think that has to color how we then look at the views that are downstream of
his, including like Post-Moleles.
There sort of isn't a strong tether in Christian tradition for them.
So yeah, I mean, from his point of view, right, like he thinks that his age is going to
and in just a few decades.
So there's this sense of like it's all coming, you know, and I mean we're in this transitional period. Yeah, right
I mean, this is a thing that's still with us and there are even God bless them some Orthodox people like oh
Yes, it's the age in the anti-Christ, you know, whatever which we talked about that last time. Yeah
but
Yeah, that's this is where this stuff comes from. Yes. Yeah, Millenarianism is not
Not not not Orthodox
There are orthodox sources, especially modern ones that are
probably clearly under some German influence.
That where you can see shades of this kind of thing,
in Brothers Kermazov,
Elder Zosobus speech about how the church will expand
to encompass the whole universe.
Is this kind of this kind of post-millennial
fiora kind of thinking a little bit?
Interesting.
So, that did rub up against the Orthodox church too
a few places.
in the, yeah, the modern period. So those are a couple of ways that the Messianic Age is talking about.
But obviously the most common way the Messianic Age is talked about is that it's the age of the Messiah, hence Messianic Age.
And that is kind of clearly talked about described with reference to the Messiah in a couple of places in Isaiah.
At least a couple of representative places in Isaiah.
Yeah.
So one is from Isaiah chapter two, verse four,
he shall judge between the nations and shall decide disputes for many peoples.
And they shall beat their swords into plough shares and their spears into pruning hooks.
Nations shall not lift up sword against nation, neither shall they learn war anymore.
anymore. So that sense of peace and the nations.
no longer be going to war with each other and and got himself deciding disputes between them.
Right. And this is the he being the Messiah. Yeah, right. The Messiah judging between the nations.
So he's governing the world. He's governing over all the nations of the world. Yep. Yep.
So there's another one from Isaiah. This is chapter 11 verses six through nine,
which spawned a thousand cheesy paintings and sculptures. It's true. It's true.
Yeah, so this is be very familiar.
The wolf shall dwell with the lamb and the leopard shall lie down with the young goat
and the calf and the lion and the fattened calf together and a little child shall lead them.
The cow and the bear shall graze their young shall lie down together
and the lion shall eat straw like the ox.
The nursing child shall play over the hole of the cobra
and the weaned child shall put his hand on the adders den.
They shall not hurt or destroy in all my body, in all my holy mountain.
For the earth shall be full of the knowledge of the Lord as the waters cover the sea. You know
It's interesting in a lot of those cheesy paintings like you never see kids sticking their hands and snakes holes. I don't know why they don't
Paint that but but more importantly
But you usually see as a lion laying down with the lamb. Yeah rather than a wolf rather than a wolf
This I don't know if you know this while they're Andrew
This verse is an example of the Mandela effect.
Ah!
Is it?
Where everybody remembers it being the lion
she'll dwell with the lamb, right?
But when you look it up at all the Bibles, it's the wolf.
Yeah, I have to imagine,
I have to imagine to somebody out there
that claiming that the Bibles are being,
like this is a thing that people say
that Bibles are being edited by some mysterious force.
Yeah, no, it's the Hadron Collider.
It caused a number of us to transition from one parallel world to another.
And so we become aware of these small differences now.
Wow, from the world in which we previously lived,
before the large Hadron Collider shifted us, right?
So like barren stain bears was spelled different.
And Sinbad was in a movie called Shazam
that came out at the same time as
Shaxx Kazam movie.
And this verse said Lion instead of Wolf.
And Nelson Mandela died in prison and was never released in that
universe.
This is well document.
That's what's called the Mandela effect.
This is well documented.
So I'm not serious.
Or am I?
What a what a world we live in.
Compared to the one we used to live in.
Anyway, so, but only some know.
Yeah, yeah.
Look it up, it'll trip you out.
There's all kinds of things you remember
that aren't actually true.
So, but, you know, that aside.
So the image here is again of a reordering of the cosmos.
Right?
There's still all these animals,
but things have been reordered.
So there's no longer enmity between animals and animals and humans and animals.
This is an image of that reordering.
And this is not just, there's this language here again of the...
which is going to come in port. We're going to talk about this more as we go forward of the knowledge of God covering the earth as
or the earth shall be full of the knowledge of the Lord.
As the waters cover the sea.
Right. And this is parallel to that that we saw in the earlier new covenant language. No one will teach his brother saying no the Lord because
everyone will know from the least to the greatest. We're going to come back to that. But again,
We can see again this same language being used here.
even though now we're talking about that age in terms of the Messiah and his
his ruling governance of the earth, the same kind of language is being used.
So again, this is another perspective on the same reality, right, of this reordered
messianic age.
And there is this sort of trope, right,
that where ages are reflected in
thousands of years, right, as in 8,000 years. And this is a tradition that you find in throughout
sort of second temple Judaism. And this is, again, don't worry young earth creation folks.
This is not the day age view as you have come to know it. But that associates ages with
the days of creation in such a way that the history of
the world, they believe will be 6,000 years.
Yeah, six days of creation, 6,000 years,
yeah, and I nicely lines up with the seventh thousand years
being the messianic age.
Yeah, right.
And this is not something that kind of gets given up after
second-temporary Judaism.
Um, in fact, among a number of Hasidic groups within
contemporary rabbinic Judaism, they have pegged this
to when the 6,000 years ends at 2240.
Wow, so AD 2040.
Joaquin de Fiori was only wrong by 980 years.
Yeah, a little less than a thousand.
So they've got to peg there.
But this is, this kind of thinking is why in the year 1000, the year AD 1000, people all over Europe sold their belongings and possessions,
and went on these pilgrimages because they were expecting in the
year 1000 for Christ's glorious appearing to take place.
That was the first great disappointment when nothing happened.
And then, of course, those of us who are elderly as covered in our introduction tonight,
remember the year 2000 in Y2K and how this was definitely going to be the end
round numbers.
And we had spent the whole previous year partying like it was 1999 with the presupposition
that we were doing so, right?
We were eating and drinking and being married because tomorrow January 1st, 2000, we were all
going to die.
And then it didn't happen.
Because of the way that Unix counts time.
Yeah.
And people really, people who weren't there don't understand this.
They don't remember how.
really was the sense of a
apocalypticism even in the yes and what was great is even in kind of like non-religious
Discourse there was this apocalypticism going on. Yes. Yes. I had I had a person yell at me and say I was sending against the Lord
by not having like food supplies that generators
For Y2K would civilization collapsed
That because I was being irresponsible
nice
Yeah, man, if you're not a prepper, you're not.
Yeah.
Like people don't realize, like people really thought, oh man, this is it, right?
I remember, I mean, when I was in seminary, there was a guy I lived next to for like a year
who had literally part of what he was, I started seminary in 2004 and he was eating down
his Y2K stash in 2004.
Yeah.
Like.
Yeah, it was a...
It was a weird time.
It was.
It really was.
But it's because of this, thousands thinking.
Right.
Yeah.
Now, if you're like an orthodox young earth creationist,
you could just ignore all that because you think
following the Byzantine chronology that the Earth is already
like 7,500 in something years old.
Yes.
So whoops.
Yeah, that whole thing's out the window.
But
That's, you'd have to worry about that.
So, yeah, so, but that's been sort of this tradition
and it's been in people's thinking,
producing sometimes wacky results.
But the core here is the idea that this is gonna be
the age in which the Messiah reigns over the Earth.
So,
the question classically
between a
that we need to answer here is, is the Messianic Age?
Because some of what we've said already,
may have caused people to think,
and some of the quotes we've read from the Old Testament,
to think that, well, the Messianic Age is sort of,
is the age to come, it is the final age,
is the age that has no end, right?
It's the ultimate age, right?
But, which means final, by the way, everybody,
It does not mean the greatest, ultimately.
It's final.
Yeah, even though this will be the greatest.
Yeah, David, we've ever known.
True.
Right, there is plenty in the scriptures to indicate
that no, the Messianic Age is actually the penultimate age.
Next, yes, next to last.
Unlike Final Fantasy, which there's nothing final about it.
I mean, what are we on now?
Final Fantasy 16 or 23?
Oh, it's not just that.
It's not just that.
They've made sequels to earlier games.
I'm dead.
It's right.
Final Fantasy 13-2, which is a different game than Final Fantasy 14.
Right. So it's even more complicated than like, is the Messianic Age the ultimate of the penultimate age?
Is it the anti-penultimate? The pre-anti-penultimate?
Yes, no. But is it ultimate or penultimate?
Yes, that's all.
Is it the final or next to the last?
Yes. So the text, the scripture's tell us if we read them closely,
but actually it's the penultimate. It's the next to last.
next to last right and a good example of that that I know we've mentioned on the show before because we come back to Daniel 7 and awful lot it seems
Is in Daniel 7
Yeah, yeah, so Daniel 7 I'm gonna skip a little bit so be verse 12 and then I'm gonna skip to verses 26 and 27
Verse 12 as for the rest of the beasts
their dominion was taken away but their lives were prolonged for a season
and a time. But the court shall sit in judgment and his dominion shall be taken away to be consumed
and destroyed to the end, and the kingdom, and the dominion, and the greatness of the kingdoms
under the whole heaven, shall be given to the people of the saints of the most high. His kingdom
shall be an everlasting kingdom, and all dominions shall serve and obey him.
Right. So there we see, right, there's this moment where the son of man is enthroned,
And
And the dominion is taken away from the beasts and given to him.
And he's ruling, right?
But the lives of the beasts is prolonged for a season and a time.
And then at the end of that season and a time, right?
That's when the final judgment happens, right?
Of the beasts.
Yeah. So the Messianic age and then there's this final judgment, right?
Yeah. And so another very clear example comes from,
from Psalm 110.
or 109 in the Greek, the first two verses.
This is, by the way, as we've mentioned before, I know on the show.
Psalm 110 or 109 is the most quoted text in the New Testament.
Yeah.
So everyone should know this one.
The Lord says to my Lord,
sit at my right hand until I make your enemies your footstool.
The Lord sends forth from Zion your mighty scepter,
rule in the midst of your enemies.
Right, and so
So this was even before the writing of the New Testament clearly accepted as being, you
know, literally it says Yahweh says to my Lord that the Lord here is talking about the
Messiah.
Such that, remember, Christ can ask the question of the scribes, right?
Whose son is the Messiah, right?
Well, if the Messiah is David's...
why does he call him Lord when, and then he quotes this verse?
Yeah.
And they don't say, oh, well, that's not talking about the Messiah.
Right.
They all agree it's talking about the Messiah.
They're kind of confounded by the question.
Right.
Because they're like, yeah, the point being like, why would David call his own son Lord?
Fathers don't call their son's Lord.
It goes the other way.
Right.
Meaning, there's a broad acceptance.
This is the Messiah.
Meaning, there's going to be a period during which the Messiah rules in the midst of his
enemies.
Yes, until they're all put at his feet.
Whereas enemies are still around.
Right.
Yeah.
And then there's going to come a time when they're going to be fully subjected to Christ
to the Messiah.
Which then, so this gets referenced in Hebrews to eight, you know, which starts with
the end of a sentence, dot, dot, dot, putting everything in subjection under his feet.
Now in putting everything in subjection to him, he left nothing outside his control.
present we do not.
yet see everything in subjection to him. Right. So Hebrews is here identifying the age in which
Hebrews is being written, right? As being this age when the Messiah is ruling over the nations,
but his enemies are still active, this penultimate age, which by the way is an answer to a question
that we get a lot, which is, why are there demons still around? Because this is the period we're in.
Yes, you know, there are some of them are still around.
Right, and so this is why as
Much as it is often framed as a problem now especially in some conversations between
Jewish people and Christians
That there's not really a problem within the scriptures themselves
About there being two comings of Christ two comings of the Messiah
Yeah, right that there's a separation between the coming of the Messiah and his enthroned
and the ultimate day of the Lord and the day of judgment.
Because this idea that there is this age
in between those two events is here in Psalm 110,
which is getting referenced all the time
in the New Testament.
It's there in Daniel, it's there in other texts as well.
We could have gone through more,
but it shows long enough.
Come on.
Um, but so that idea is already, yeah.
I don't ever want to say that.
Is it really long enough?
Never.
No.
At some point, at some point, I'm now calling this out live on the air.
Oh no.
It's father.
Yeah, father is just getting nervous.
At some point, I want to pick a charity and I want to do a Lord of Spirits marathon.
Where we just pick a night and we just keep going.
Until people stop giving.
We just broadcast for like eight or 10 hours or so.
Yeah, see the problem
is that we have people in other countries who are listening and will get up and will keep
going. Meanwhile, I will not be going to sleep. Yeah. We could do that. I will not soon,
not soon. Maybe not today, maybe not tomorrow. Yes. But someday and for the rest of our lives,
not. That's right. Cause I will die on here. Well, what a way to go out. Yeah. That blazes
Glory. Praising money for good.
cause. Yeah. I mean, that's way better than like collapsing in a dance marathon, right?
Which you've done that, right? A dance marathon? Yeah. No, I'm not done in dance. But you are
like a gold medalist in dance. I am a gold medal winning ballroom dancer. But you're thinking of
Fonzie winning the dance marathon. Remember, you did the Russian Cosac dance at the end when he got his
second win. Why do I remember that?
Okay, we're going off the rails.
Yes, so.
Right.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, right.
Like the messianic age is the age that's between these two events, but it's not in the
future still.
Like the messianic age is not in the future because like, you know, again, if everybody
pulls out their clearance, larkin posters, the dispensationalism has to invent this other
age called the church age.
Right.
It is a horrendous this.
Right, this sort of weird interjection because the biblical timeline of right great tribulation
Daniel, Messianic age age to come is so clear. Right. And so if you're going to push the
Messianic age into the future, you've got to find some way to put this square peg into
the round hole that's left, right? Yeah.
of this present age in which we're living in,
despite the fact that, again, we saw hebre...
There are plenty more examples.
Brethren, these are the last days.
Right?
This is the last age.
This is the last time period.
Again and again in the New Testament scriptures, clearly identifying us as being in this Messianic
age.
And part of the character of the Messianic age is that Christ is ruling, but He's ruling
in the midst of His enemies.
In the midst of His enemies.
Yeah.
I think it ain't over.
It ain't over.
Yeah.
All right.
We're going to take our final break and we'll be right back with the third half of the Lord
of spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part
of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Ancient Faith Radio was brought to you by our listeners
with help from the University of St. Catherine.
The University of St. Catherine is an accredited orthodox
Orthodox Christian
institution, offering undergraduate and graduate degree programs.
In addition to its online 15-month MA and Orthodox Christian theology, it offers over 20 Bachelor
of Arts and Bachelor of Science degrees in Arts and Humanities, Business, Management and
Economics, Kinesiology, and Natural Sciences.
Scholarships are available for Orthodox students.
We are still accepting students for the fall of 2023.
more about our accredited, affordable, nationally recognized.
at usk.edu or phone 760-471-1316.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back everybody.
So, you know, related to all this,
this. I actually just...
to share a text that my wife just sent me while we were on the air here because it's very
related. I don't know that she's listening to the show. She's not with me.
Was it a gift of Fonzie doing the Cossack dance because that would be an amazing coincidence?
That would be great, wouldn't it? No, so she apparently was talking to our six-year-old son
and told him the story of Adam and Eve and then, you know, Paradise and so forth and explained that,
that, you know.
the life of the age to come, we get to be, we get to be in paradise again, right? And
she told him that we get to eat all the fruit. And apparently he got like really upset when
she said this. And so she asked him, why, like, why are you so unhappy? He says he didn't
want, he doesn't want fruit. And so she asked him, what do you want to eat in heaven? And
And he said corn dogs.
So there you are.
Paradise from the mind of my six-year-old son.
is about corn dogs. Corn dogs are good. They are a staple. If you go and get the state fair corn dogs
in the freezer section of your local Walmart, they're best if you oven bake them. I can feel my
arteries stopping right now. If you put them in the microwave, it's just like this spongy nitrite
sickle. How about deep fry? Deep fry. Deep fry is good. If you have an air fryer, that's really peak.
And then if you if you're one of those people who knows and if you know you know you got to get the lemonade and the yellow mustard
Go on for the hotdog on a stick. There you go
Yeah
So someday if he ever listens to this show
He probably won't but if he ever does
I'm sure he'll giggle. This was the moment. Yes, exactly. You became famous exactly
Exactly, exactly.
Yeah.
So, all right, part three, yes, the third half.
And so, we sort of ended talking about the difficulty of projecting the Messianic age
into the future, right, which not just dispensationalism does, but any form of pre-millennialism
does, right, by sort of by definition, moves that Messianic age forward and creates this,
this middle part.
So what we're mainly going to be talking about in the third half.
is kiliasum. And kiliasum, as we're going to explain, is not exactly pre-millennialism,
but kiliasum is a really a category of views in early Christianity. By early Christianity,
we're talking about second-third century. Yeah, super. And even in the fourth and fifth centuries.
Christianity named from...
which means a thousand that believed in, basically believed that that Messianic age was in the future.
Yeah, and if you've never heard this far, it's not allowed before, the word looks like chileism,
because it's usually spelled with a CH. Yeah, it's chileism, because that CH represents
the Greek letter, he, so it's chileism. Although, although somebody out there needs to start
start him.
millennial chili brand. There we go. That would be good.
Based on this. So, uh, and where does that view come from? Right?
Um, this, this view, it ultimately pretty much gets condemned by the church.
Right. And, and there are continuity and discontinuities between it and
Modern premalalism ultimately gets
condemned by the church. But it's, you know, I hesitate to call it a
heresy because it's not a heresy in the same sense as like
Aryanism. Yeah, it's not a Christological heresy.
Christological heresy is not a Tritarian heresy, right? It's
it's so it's not in that category. It's more in the category of
theological error. Yeah, it's an eschatological error, right?
And so...
So it is condemned, right?
But it is, yeah, it's in that category of this is wrong, not in the category of, you
know, someone trying to set up a sect outside the church.
Now that said, as we're going to see, there are a number of heretical groups that are heretical
for other reasons that are also killiasts where this is part of their views.
which doesn't help it. But so where does it come from? Right? So most of the kind of
trinitarian heresies and crystallological heresies find their origin in some rejection of the orthodox
view, right? Either because someone finds that the orthodox view to be nonsensical or doesn't
understand it or misunderstands it or has some reason why they want to reject.
the traditional Orthodox view,
whereas this view grows up a little differently.
It has a little bit different genealogy,
sort of as kilesum forms.
It's really grounded originally in the kind of thinking
that led the Pharisees within
second-table Judaism to hold to the bodily resurrection.
Hmm.
So we're sort of coming back to the bodily resurrection.
So as you know, even if you've just read the book of Acts,
right, they're sort of the famous scene in the book of Acts,
the Acts of the Apostles, where St. Paul is confronted by a mixed group of Pharisees and Sadducees.
And so he kind of throws up a distraction by saying,
oh, I'm here because of the resurrection,
because the Pharisees believe in the resurrection and the Sadduce,
right, to get some all sort of fighting amongst themselves about it.
I'm sorry.
So the fact that this is a specifically a ferrousaic belief within the various sex, right?
This is one of the identifying beliefs of the Pharisees.
And they come to hold to the importance of the bodily resurrection, the importance of
affirming the bodily resurrection, which is present there as far back as Job, at least
in the Hebrew.
by the way.
Greek Bible folks. I like Greek Old Testament tradition as much as anybody, but the Hebrew
of Job contains a much firmer specific declaration of the bodily resurrection than the Greek does.
So this is an element, but the furnaces are going to
sit on the importance of this.
Right?
This is not just some kind of speculative hope or something, but this is
an important, this is doctrinally important.
It's dogma, basically.
And that's because of their understanding of justice.
Right?
And you can see the kind of tension that they're wanting to resolve,
for example, when you compare Psalm 1 and Psalm 2.
Right, and someone in...
have the same numbers in Hebrew and Greek. It's not Psalm 0 and 1 in what it to what.
So, Psalm 1 is very much in the vein of the righteous man is like a tree planted by a river
and the wicked man is blown away. The righteous prosper the wicked parish.
right? Boom, yes, we all agree that's the way things should be. That's
the order in the world. And then you get to solve too. And it's like, how long will the
wicked prosper? Because we look around in the world that we see that a lot of times that's
not the case, right? That the righteous are oppressed and the righteous suffer. And the wicked
seem in this life to prosper. A lot of them die without sort of getting their come-up ends without
without there being any kind of justice
for their wickedness, right?
And from that perspective,
from a Jewish perspective that's immersed deep in the Hebrew Scriptures,
this is a problem that has to be resolved. And it can't just be resolved by
saying, well, they go to heaven somewhere or they have a pleasant afterlife and
these other people have a bad afterlife, right? That kind of nebulous spiritual
answer is unreal to them, right? And this is a place where this kind of thinking
really is.
is directly antithetical to Platinism.
So for Plato, with other places,
we talked about the bodily resurrection
tonight was in terms of St. Augustine's view of history.
But, you know, for Plato, the spiritual,
the immaterial, the invisible, the internal,
is the most real.
And the physical of the material is the least real.
Right, it's like a shadow of an image, right?
and this is the reverse.
Right. So just some kind of happy,
ephemeral afterlife is not does not solve the problem.
Right. Of a righteous person having received curses
rather than blessings. Yeah. Right. And and a wicked person
receiving blessings rather than curses. Yeah. That that
ultimately the bodily resurrection is grounded in the
material creation. Right. That the ordering of creation, the
order in the world has to be restored. Yeah.
And that...
has to be restored objectively, but has to function properly after being restored.
Yeah.
Right.
And so, this bodily resurrection, this transformation, this transfiguration of the cosmos has to
happen in order for that to happen, right, in order for that to be real.
So the bodily resurrection becomes chiefly important because it becomes an affirmation of the
the justice of God.
and of the goodness of God, and that God speaks the truth in the Torah when he promises blessings
for obedience and righteousness and curses for disobedience and wickedness.
And this understanding of resurrection is at play in the early homilies, the early sermons
we have in the Book of Acts.
especially Saint Peter's, when he talks about Christ's resurrection.
Right. That Christ claimed to be the Messiah. He was vindicated when he was raised from the dead.
He was condemned, right. As a liar, he was condemned as a wicked man, along with other
wicked men, right, thieves, but by the resurrection he was vindicated, right? He was shown...
to be the Messiah by being raised from the dead. That's working off of this idea, this
fair-sake Jewish idea, of what the bodily resurrection represents and how it works.
So the Kilias are taking this kind of idea. They're taking this kind of idea and saying,
Therefore,
Right, the saints, the martyrs, right?
He spoke, they have to have this sort of justice,
these sort of blessings in this world,
in this earth, this material way.
Right? And especially as Christianity is
budding up against Nosticism and Nosticism's
All two full embrace of Platonism and
rejection of the value of the material, even going further than Plato and say the material is actually evil.
Yeah, not just a shadow of an image, but actually evil, actually bad, right, and denial of the physicality of salvation.
They see affirming kiliasum, affirming this future material messianic age in this world, right, as being
the key to rejecting, to rejecting.
the key to establishing the justice of God and the truth of God's promises in the same kind of
way that the Pharisees did. It's built off the same logic
right
But the problem is and this is something we've seen a lot
Right, this is something we've seen a lot is that all too often
often when a
view whether it's a heresy or just a wrong view or bad theology rises up. There's a tendency for some
of those opposing it to not question the basis of that theology but to accept the basis and take
the other side. So an example of that that we've talked about before since I've been trying to be
be nice so far to the younger creationists.
I'll be a little less nice now.
I should have a little bit of cred with them that I can now squander.
We've talked about how you have sort of the rise of modernism
and the subjection of the text of scripture and things to modern science as it's
understood in any particular era. And therefore the discounting of the veracity of the scriptures,
the reading of the scriptures in a very materialistic way.
by what has it various times been called Protestant liberalism or you know the theology that comes out of 19th century Germany right this is
agreeably bad. But when the modernist fundamentalist crisis happens in the United States
the fundamentalists
does not mean calling them that this is what they called themselves at the time yes
The fundamentalists do not try to go to a pre-modern reading of
scripture, do not reject the basic way of reading the Bible in this sort of materialist,
literalist way. Do not reject any of that. They try to use the same methodology and come
to the opposite conclusions. And that's where you get young earth creation. Yeah. Right.
So both of those views are fundamentally modernist. Right. As we've said on the show before,
Well, you get the same kind of thing here with cheliasm.
So you have kind of nostic...
and Gnostic tinge versions of Christian eschatology,
which strip away the material element of salvation,
the transformation of this world, the bodily resurrection,
either deny it or deemphasize it,
maybe even ignore it,
and spiritualize it all, or platenize it all.
And over against that the kill yeah
rather than questioning the separation of the spiritual and material kingdoms.
Right? Because focusing on the spiritual is based on separating those two ideas
and then either rejecting one or saying one is more important or however that works out.
But there's a separation implied.
Rather than questioning that separation and trying to bring them back together,
which is what the Orthodox Party did, was continued to hold them together,
They X
except that these are two separate things,
and just affirm the material and physical apart,
and deny or de-emphasize the spiritual part.
Right.
They say, no, it's just the literal and the material, right?
Christ being enthroned at the right hand of God
doesn't quote unquote count as his ruling the world.
He's got to come back and rule it here physically.
Yeah.
I think it doesn't seem to be hucky.
So therefore it must not have happened.
Right.
And so it's a misguided right of taking the other option based on faulty presuppositions rather
than questioning the presuppositions.
And I do have to say, I do have to say, this is one of the first things I posted on my blog
that got people all worked up is when I said, the idea of people going to heaven or hell
when they die as a sub-Christian eschatology.
the phrase, I use, oh, people went ballistic.
But the common view, your average person on the street, right,
who may or may not fully identify as a Christian, if you ask them,
what happens when you die, you get, you go to heaven or you go to hell for how long?
Oh, for eternity.
Right.
Yeah.
Bodily resurrection, anybody.
I mean, this is what's represented in pop culture that ever deals with this.
I can, it's your big slits.
Yeah.
So Harold Bloom was basically right.
The average Christian in the United States is anostec.
Yeah.
I would love it if we could say, if someone says, well, he's in a better place now.
We could say for now.
Yeah.
He's going to be an even better place in the future.
Certainly here.
Right.
Because here's going to get a lot better.
Yeah, yeah, and read Robin Phil
a recent book if you want more help extracting yourself from narcissism.
Yeah, and so the within kiliasum,
sort of this material rule of Christ gets postponed.
And so in certain ways,
this represents a point of continuity with modern pre-millennialism.
Right.
because
Well, they also have a comment that they have a literal,
they tend to take it as a literal thousand years,
rather than just as an age, right?
The thousand years is representing an age.
But also that there is this physical, earthly element
of it and that it is postponed into the future.
Yeah, yeah.
That said, there's a major point,
there are a few points of discontinuity.
The biggest point of discontinuity
Thank you very much.
that the Kilias, when they talked about an earthly paradise, meant an earthly paradise.
Right.
Like, it's like heaven in the Quran.
Like, you having lots of kids and eating sumptuously every day, extra desserts and drinking tons
and tons of wine, which no good pre-millennialist Baptist would be on board with.
Right.
Never get at that.
Yeah, right. Yeah. And
you living for hundreds of years, right?
It's very much earthly paradise, right?
In ancient Kiliasum, and modern premillennialism
is a little more theological
and spiritually sophisticated than that, right?
In terms of how they see it.
There's also a different focus
in that a lot of the focus in modern premillennialism
is on is
Not on modern primal journalism does not focus on this idea of reward for having lived
righteously and done good.
And that's because it's operating in Protestant circles.
Yes, right.
Right.
So there aren't people who have done all this good and been unrewarded.
It's works.
Faith versus works.
Right.
It tends to be especially in the dispensationalist side.
Right?
to what's sometimes called historic premillennialism or other adjectives.
It's more oriented toward particular promises to national Israel.
And the modern nation state of Israel is often considered to be the same entity as the
Israel of the Bible.
Yeah, just kind of silly.
But.
Yeah, we don't need to go into all that, but yeah, but suffice to say a lot of people living in the
modern nation state of Israel do not regard what they're doing as being identical to the Israel of the
Bible. A lot of Jewish people don't think it's right. Right. Right. Um, yeah. So, um, yeah. So
that's a discontinuity, right. Uh, ancient kilesh, it was not really concerned with that.
Right, there was no-
of this stuff about rabbinic Judaism, right, or there being a nation-state of Israel in the
future or any of that, right, in ancient Kileshom. So there are clear separations there.
And what really ends up getting, I mean, Kileshom probably, this is conjectural, this is alternate
history, right? So unless the large
Hadron Collider helps me. I won't know for sure. But, uh,
Kilias might have just sort of faded away as an incorrect view.
Right. If it hadn't gotten associated as we mentioned with certain
other ancient heretical groups who became Kilias,
primarily in this case,
montanous and his followers.
Yeah.
Montanism sometimes referred to as the pontic heresy.
Yeah
Look them up, everybody. They are a wacky, fun, interesting wacky.
Well, I do have to say, okay, so what of the, what of the fascinating things of this age of
the internet and the availability of information is that some sectarian groups in the modern world
have decided to embrace ancient heresies as their historical ancestors.
Oh, I know. Well, I mean, but, but so even prior, even prior to the wide
wacky world
the inner webs, you get landmarkism.
Trilablod. Yeah. Yeah. Trilablod stuff, which is like everybody
who wasn't Catholic in the ancient world is some kind of Baptist.
Yes. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. But this is more I'm thinking more of how
some of the Jehovah's Witnesses now are trying to say, Oh, yeah,
we're in continuity with the Aryans. Right. Right. And trying to
sort of embrace that to give them self a sense of history. We're
not a group that spawned in the 20th century.
off the side of evangelical Protestantism in the United States. No, we have this ancient heritage of the Aryans, right?
So lately I have seen this a bunch
people from charismatic and penicostal groups
going to the Monteneges. Yeah, don't go there penicostal friends. Yes, it's only sadness and
presenting
The Monteneges is being some kind of early charismatic groups because there are accounts that talk about them having glossololia
which is...
what is in the modern day called speaking in tongues.
Yeah.
And some other manifestations like that, okay.
But here's what we have to be clear about, okay.
The montenists, which is what Tritolian became,
which is why he's not Saint Tritolian.
That's right.
Believed that the person they're named after,
Montana's, was the parakeet.
Yes.
Promised by Christ.
And who would come out of him?
And he hung around with these two prophetesses.
Yes, he traveled with two female pro...
who he roamed with.
Right.
It's a bad scene.
You don't want to go there.
Pedicostal friends.
As a general rule,
all cults become sex cults.
I'm just.
It's, it's true.
So.
Yeah.
So this is not a guy you want to
pin your lineage on.
Right.
Like you're better off being a 20
century phenomenon than being
connected to the mountainous.
Yep.
But, right, so the problem with the mountainous
was not primarily that they were kill-ass.
They just also were kill-ass.
Yes.
And so, but that being a part of their whole new you, right,
when the church fathers wrote against
one of these heretical groups, they kind of went full-bore,
right, kind of went after everything wrong, right.
They didn't say, well, they're also wrong about this,
that and the other, but those aren't as important.
They just...
right, went to the wall.
Here's everything they're wrong about,
and they're wrong about everything, right?
And so this is how Kilias' men's
up kind of getting broadly condemned.
And they're not the only group.
They're just maybe the most prominent group
that were Kilias.
A lot of the Appalainarians were also Kilias.
So it gets kind of a bad rap in that way, right?
Yeah, not that we're saying it's good, but.
And yeah, yeah, it's just, like I said,
I
would have just been an error and not like a major heresy thing if it hadn't ended up getting associated with these
heretical groups. And sort of as evidence of that, both St. Jerome and St. Andrew of Cesaria took
commentaries on the book of Revelation that had been written by Kilias and it had them to take out the
and then put them out under their own names.
As one does.
Right.
But so, and that's, you know, fifth century, sixth century, right?
Fifth century, the west, sixth century, the east, right?
These are fathers who are saying, hey, if it weren't for the killi as of, there's a lot
of good stuff here, right?
Yeah, right.
I submit to you, they would not have done the same with an Aryan text.
No.
Or an historian text, right?
Or fill in the blank, right?
It's that, yeah, I think it's that sense of, oh, well, there's some problems with this.
We can fix them.
Right, we'll just...
cross out all the errors, right, and keep the rest. And I'll add a little bit here there to fill out where I took out the errors with the correct view, right?
So that's evidence that it was sort of treated differently by the church fathers, even though again, we're not allowed to talk about patristics on this show.
Then, then, heresy hered, crystallological heresies are trititarian heresies.
So that's it.
Having said all that.
It is a commonplace of the world, both on popular and academic levels, to say that St.
Irenaeus, amongst other church fathers, but we're just going to talk about St.
Irenaeus right now.
That St. Irenaeus was a kill-assed.
Yes.
And that he made this unfortunate error and then later on, you know, like, we'll excuse
him for this, because the church only later on realized that this was really an error.
Yeah
or took the time to condemn it or whatever.
Yeah.
And other weird arguments.
But yeah.
Yeah.
We're very sad.
Here.
Nass.
I tried to figure out like when people
started saying this about him, I
couldn't I couldn't find anything really.
And I don't know.
You know, listeners, if you know, like who's
a pre-modern person.
Yeah.
Who says this about saying here.
Nass.
We're not saying there isn't one, but we haven't found that
person.
We haven't found that one yet, so.
As far as we can tell, this is a modern thing to say that he was a killiast.
Yeah, so what what what Father Stephen did as he was researching for this is he went and found all
the passages from St. Irenaus that people who are either using it to accuse him or are using it to
say to enlist him on their killiast side. Yes. Right. All the folks they give to make their case.
right right because i have long contended that he is not a kill a
Yes, right. So when I say that people give me the hairy eyeball like everyone knows he is right well, okay
Yeah, so so fathers didn't put these in front of me and was best and basically said okay these are the passages that
You know, so I'm just I just looked at them cold when we were briefing for this right so I'm gonna
We're gonna go through them. We're not gonna spend a lot of time on them because it would that would be like a whole episode
Probably right record to banal it word by word or anything. Yeah, just to kind of get this on the record
Here.
Um, right. Okay. And I said, okay, before you start, what I said to father Andrew was,
like if this was a court case, and they presented these quotes as their evidence, right?
I would not present a case. I would move that the judge dismissed the case because they
haven't met their burden of proof. Yeah. I don't think there's anything in any of these quotes
that they're using to say he's a killiast that even suggests he's a killiast. Right. I,
Yeah, I look so stupid.
And my response was kind of like, wait, what?
For, I mean, some of them you can kind of maybe
sort of.
If you read it sideways, yeah.
Yeah, but oh, yeah.
So spoilers everybody.
OK, so here's the first one.
These are all from, these are all from against heresies.
Yeah.
So this is from book five, 32, one.
These are all from book five, all of the 30s in the sections.
Yeah.
So 32.
that one, in as much therefore as the opinions of certain people are derived from heretical
discourses. They are both ignorant of God's dispensations and of the mystery of the resurrection
of the just and of the kingdom, which is the commencement of incorruption by means of
which kingdom those who shall be worthy are accustomed gradually to partake of the divine
nature. I just I can't even see it in that and actually he talks about theosis here.
Right. Right. And notice notice he says by means of which kingdom those who shall be worthy are accustomed
Gradually to the partake of the divine nature meaning this is happening now suggesting that the kingdom is going on now
Yeah, yeah, so it's kind of like actually this is arguing for the other side. Yes
Okay, next
This is from 35.1
If any however shall endeavor to
allegorize prophecies of this kind. They will not be found consistent with them.
themselves in all points and will be
confuted by the teaching of the very
expressions in question.
So this was another one that just
let me stumped.
And it turns out that because he
says something against the idea of
allegorizing prophecies, that must
mean that he is a biblical
literate in the modern
prophecy.
Yes, he is taking everything
perfectly literally.
Yeah, literalist.
Yeah, yeah, which, you know,
therefore means he should be
acquitted.
Okay.
Right.
All right.
again, like, doesn't...
doesn't hold up. Okay, 36.23. The present world would not be annihilated, though the present
corruptible state would give way to an incorruptible state where nothing grows old or loses its
freshness. Those that produce a hundredfold would go up to heaven, those that produce 60fold
to paradise, those that produce 30fold to the city. And that means that he being the New Jerusalem.
New Jerusalem, right. So like the only way that this could work is if you decide that there is
in the
future. Again, like this earthly paradise that we were talking about, right? Like if you
presume that's what that's true. And then you read this, you say, oh, this might sort of
fit into that. But he says the present world is not going to be annihilated, that it's going
to, that it's just an corruptible state. And there's an incorruptible state.
And that's what they're saying makes him a kill. He asked. Right. Which like that's not distinctive
to kiliasm right right people people
All Christians should believe in the bodily resurrection and the transfiguration of this world.
Right. Right. This is just normal standard. This is Christianity.
Yeah. Right.
Okay. Then he has sort of that bit about going to heaven, paradise, the New Jerusalem.
He's talking about sort of levels of reward in heaven.
Yeah. So in other words, I mean, this is something that we believe that some saints kind of shine
more brightly than others. That heaven there meaning the age to come. Right. Levels of reward in the
the edge to come.
Yeah.
Okay, so here's another one. Again, these are all from book five. This is 36.2. The
presbyters, the disciples of the apostles affirm that this is the gradation and
arrangement of those who are saved and that they advance through steps of this
nature also that they ascend through the Spirit to the Son and through the Son
to the Father and that in due time the Son will yield up his work to the Father.
I'm still stumped at this one. Like how is I don't I don't
I just don't so I think the idea is he's a killiast because see in due time the Sun will yield up his work to the Father.
And that due time is I guess the Millennium is I guess the thousand years.
Okay.
Sure.
All right, click it through.
Like we said, you have to really stretch this to make it even fit
kiliasum. Let alone, oh, see, look, he's a kiliasum.
to what I like.
Yeah, I mean, again, these are the quotes that are used to prove this point.
But they use, these aren't quotes I picked to refute it.
These are the quotes they use to try to say he's a kill yes.
Yeah, yeah.
Okay, so here's one from 32.1, for it is just that in that very creation in which they
toiled or were afflicted being proved in every way by suffering, they should receive
the reward of their suffering.
And then in the creation in which they were slain be revived again.
that in the creation in which they endured servitude and that they should reign.
which, again, this is just a affirmation of the bodily resurrection.
Yes.
Like, that's what's going on here.
Okay.
Yeah.
All right.
Just a couple more, everybody.
A few more.
So this is from part 38.
For in as many days as this world was made, in so many thousand years, still it be concluded.
Okay.
Here we go.
yet, right? And for this...
The first reason the Scripture says,
thus the heaven and the earth were finished
and all their adornment,
and God brought to a conclusion upon the sixth day
of the works that He had made,
and God rested upon the seventh day from all His works.
This is an account of the things formerly created,
as also it is a prophecy of what is to come.
For the day of the Lord is as a thousand years,
and in six days, created things were completed,
it is evident therefore that they will come to an end
at the six thousand years.
So, I mean, this just preserves this
How's the year's equals?
the Navy version. Second double Judaism. Yeah. Yeah. I mean, again, they did not kill you. Yeah. Right.
Unless you think, unless you think like the Pharisees were all pre-millidialists. Yeah. Good luck
arguing that one. Right. Right. Okay. Another one, again, from Book 5 chapter, or part 33,
Christ, after he had given thanks while holding the cup and a drunk of it and given it to the
the disciples.
said to them, but I say unto you, I will not drink henceforth of the fruit of this vine until
that day when I drink it new with you in my father's kingdom. Thus then, he will himself renew
the inheritance of the earth and will reorganize the mystery of the glory of his sons, as David says,
he who hath renewed the face of the earth. He promised to drink of the fruit of the vine with his
disciples, thus indicating both on these points the inheritance of the earth in which the new fruit
to the vine is drunk and the resurrection of his disciples in the flesh.
For the new flesh which rises again is the same which also received the new cup.
And he cannot by any means be understood as drinking of the fruit of the vine when settled
down with his disciples above in a super celestial place nor again are they who drink it
devoid of flesh, for to drink of that which flows from the vine pertains to flesh and not
spirit.
So you could read this in the Kilesh way, I guess, saying that this eschatological
you, Chris, will only happen. I don't know. It's my I'm falling apart trying to make it work
really, really aesthetically. It's very, it's very, it's the information of the bodily
resurrection. Like this is going to happen in the body. Right. It's the bodily resurrection.
That's all it's all you saw. It's the bodily resurrection. And why? This is against
heresy. She's arguing against the no sticks who didn't believe in the bodily resurrection.
Yeah. Yeah.
He's not arguing with Amalini, Modern Amalini.
He's arguing with, right?
Right.
Dostics, and he's affirming over against them
the bodily resurrection.
This is nothing to do with kiliasum.
Yeah.
Okay, so this is the final one.
This is probably the funnest one in terms of the language that he uses.
It's pretty, it's really, it is extra as the kids say these days.
So, this is book five, part 33.
The elders who saw John the disciple.
Lord, related, that they had heard from him how the Lord used to teach in regards to those
times and say, the days will come in which vines shall grow, each having ten thousand branches,
and in each branch ten thousand twigs, and in each true twig ten thousand shoots,
and in each one of the shoots ten thousand clusters, and on every one of the clusters ten thousand
grapes, and every grape when pressed will give five and twenty matrides of wine, of wine,
And when any one of the saints so lay hold of a cluster
another chakrai out, I am a better cluster. Take me, bless the Lord through me.
And like manner the Lord declared that a grain of wheat would produce 10,000 years, and that
every year should have 10,000 grains, and every grain would yield 10 pounds of clear, pure
fine flour, and that all other fruit-bearing trees and seeds and grass would produce in
similar proportions. Everybody's out there is doing the math right now.
And clearly, clearly.
This is quoting Christ Christ minute literally
That's way have to do the math. Yes
Figure out how much how much wine is this
Flower but more right more pointily right so the way in which this is seen by some people to kill
As is the whole element of the kill is believing in this earthly paradise
Yeah, right so see looking talking about how there's gonna be this plenty of wine and plenty of flour
and grain and food. Right.
By the way, if anyone's wondering, a matrides is an ancient Greek unit of liquid measurement
equivalent to 39.3 liters. So that is okay. So factor that into your math. What do you
tell me? Why? And you can get it's 25 times that every grape. Yes. There's 10,000 of those
of the, yeah. That is a lot of wine. There is someone will do that math and said to
do it. Yeah, of course.
right in we want to hear from you. So but more importantly, this is a reference to another text.
This is a reference to 1st, Enoch 10 vs. 19.
All my stars.
Right. And anybody who's read St. Irenaeus knows St. Irenaeus had read the book of Enoch.
Yes, a lot. Right. He has the whole watcher story and they have
preaching, right? You're familiar with this text, right? What he's changed here is that the
speaker is the Lord like God in Firsteanek. And here the speaker is the Lord Jesus. So St.
Your NAS is saying that Jesus was the speaker in Prostinic.
Hmm.
Yeah. Is what he's doing.
here. And in Firsteanick, this is talking about the Messianic age.
Yeah. He expands a little bit on it too. There's a lot more math in his version.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Right. More sort of a sort of a Tirek map. Right. So that's it.
That's the case. Those are the quotes based on which it is quote unquote common knowledge
that say Irenaeus was a killiest.
No dogs are hunting.
Yeah, that means to me there is no evidence that St. Aaron A.S. was a Kiliast.
Right, unless you think anyone who believes that the bodily resurrection is de facto a Kiliast, which I present is not the case.
That makes you a Christian.
Yeah.
So, stop saying that.
If you hear someone saying that say citations needed and if they bring up any of these passages you could point out to
them, they don't prove what they think they prove. Right.
Yeah, it just. Yeah, doesn't so now as we come to the end of the third half,
let's talk about Revelation, chapter 20 in the millennium.
The actual topic of this episode. Yes.
Welcome. Yeah. Okay. So this is, this is the, the passage it talks about this
Revelation 20 verses 1 through 8.
He who endures to the end shall hear about the topic.
Then I saw an angel coming down from heaven holding in his hand the key to the bottomless pit and a great chain.
And he seized the dragon that ancient serpent who is the devil and Satan and bound him for a thousand years and threw him into the pit and shut it and sealed it over him
so that he might not deceive the nations any longer until a thousand years were ended.
And
that he must be released for a little while.
Then I saw thrones and seated on them were those to whom the authority to judge was committed.
Also I saw the souls of those who had been beheaded for the testimony of Jesus and for the
Word of God, and those who had not worshiped the beast or its image and had not received
its mark on their foreheads or their hands.
They came to life and reigned with Christ for a thousand years.
The rest of the dead did not come to life until the thousand years were ended.
This is the first...
resurrection. Blessed and holy is the one who shares in the first resurrection. Over such, the
second death has no power, but they will be priests of God and of Christ, and they will reign with
him for a thousand years. And when the thousand years are ended, Satan will be released from his
prison, and will come out to deceive the nations that are at the four corners of the earth,
Gog and May Gog, to gather them for battle. Their number is like the send of the sea.
So
The reason we're doing this last is not just Lord of Spirit's tradition.
Right.
It's that with everything we've gone over the preceding three hours, right?
To me at least, hopefully, if we haven't put you to sleep, right, if you've endured,
And we read that now with that background.
It's pretty clear what it's talking about.
Right. If we had started out by reading it, then we would have gotten into all the ambiguity
of, well, this group reads it this way, and that group reads it that way. And how do we
mitigate between the two? And they use these other proofdits. But having laid out all the
background when you read it, and you read it in light of Daniel 7, and you read it in
light of Jeremiah 31 and Ezekiel and Isaiah, right? And these other things we've read in
Psalm 110 and everything else. It's pretty obvious, right? What St. John is talking about.
here, right? So there is this
binding of the devil, right, this binding of Satan
where he's thrown in the pit and sealed for this age, this era, right? And of course
this is language
that
this is language that Christ used about
binding the strong man and pillaging
Pillaging his wares.
This is in the icon of the resurrection.
and the harrowing of Hades, right, that you'll find in pretty much every Orthodox church,
right, the devil being bound, the devil being restricted. But this is just another way
of talking about what happens in Daniel when the dominion is stripped away from the
beast and given to the Son of Man who is enthroned.
Yeah.
Right. And remember that whole Daniel passage about the enthronement of the Son of Man begins
with, Thrones were set. Well, look at verse 4 of chapter 20. Then I saw Throne
.
Yeah, I mean, this just echoes what is it Daniel seven? Yeah, right?
and
Right so the body of the devil and then you have this talk of the first resurrection
the souls of those who had been been beheaded for the test I'd use the martyrs right the saints those who had not
worshiped the beast right those who had they came to life and they reigned with Christ for the thousand years
the rest of the dead afterwards
This is the first resurrection, right?
So
So a pretty many other Achilles-esque kind of view wants to make the first resurrection,
a first bodily resurrection, and then there's another bodily resurrection.
But is that really the first resurrection?
Remember what Christ says to the Sadducees who come and ask him about famously about seven
or one bride for seven brothers.
Seven brothers? Yeah.
one bride for seven brothers. He says to them, as to the resurrection,
God says, I am the God of Abraham, end of Isaac, and of Jacob. I am not the God of the dead,
but of the living, which means that Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob are resurrected, resurrected,
and he doesn't mean bodily. Yeah, because Abraham is still in his tomb, his body is still in his tomb.
Right, Christ had not been bottled in.
resurrected yet. When he said that, right, but he's still resurrected. So this is the first resurrection.
Right. The soul being made alive in its connection to God. See our soul episode. Right.
This is the first resurrection and they rule and reign with Christ for this Messianic era during
which Christ is ruling what in the midst of his enemies. According to Daniel, according to
to Psalm 110 and all the places it cited in the New Testament.
right? And they reign and they service priests. They're priestly
service as we've talked about before on the show, right? This is a
service of intercession. If Christ isn't ruling in the midst of
his enemies, then what's what's going on with intercessions?
Yeah, why? Why would you have to make intercessions for those on
earth? Yeah, right? And then it's after this, right? It's after
after this, that not only the rest of the dead are raised, but the
there is this final rebellion, right, where those who were bound are finally judged, a law,
Daniel seven, right? But another reason why we know what the first resurrection is talking
about is the fact that in verse six, saying John feels the need to point out that those
who share in the first resurrection are blessed in holy. Yeah, because someone might think
that they're not.
Be greater.
Their debt is correct to get contrary.
review, right? Yeah. Yeah. And why would that be? Well, I mean, we see this in First
Thessalonians, frankly, St. Paul talks about this, this idea that these people have been
martyred, right? These people have suffered for Christ. These people are dead, right?
But surely failure to earthly eyes. Yeah. And they're failure. And they must be of some
lesser caliber than those who will still be alive at the time that Christ, right, has
is glorious appearing. Right? These must be a curse.
because they died. Sometimes they died very young. They were killed violently.
Yeah. Yeah. I know. I mean, yeah.
And so not only does St. John say it here, but like, you know, if you go to
Vespers and the Orthodox Church for feasts, usually of martyrs and various
other saints, you'll sometimes hear this passage from the wisdom of Solomon,
chapter three, but the souls of the righteous are in the hand of God and no
torment will ever touch them. And the eyes of the foolish, they seem to have
died and their departure was thought to be an affliction.
and they're going from us to be their destruction,
but they are at peace,
for though in the sight of men they were punished,
their hope is full of immortality.
So it's making the same point
that St. John is making there in Revelation 20.
Right.
And the prokiminon before the epistle reading
in Orthodox funeral service,
I know that just went over the heads of the people
who've never been to an Orthodox service,
but is blessed is he whom thou hast chosen
and taken O Lord?
Yeah.
This person who is
died who was here who were having the funeral for who were mourning, this person is blessed
because of the destiny they have in Christ, which is the same thing blessed in holy are
those who participate in the first resurrection, right? That that St. John is saying here, right?
And so saying that Christ's kingdom is now, that Christ is right now ruling and writing
in the midst of his enemies is not saying, oh Christ just has some
kind of spiritual kingdom or some kind of allegorical kingdom or some kind of, right, wu wu
theoretical kingdom or, you know, he's on the throne in my heart or whatever else, right?
That's not what it is saying, right? That's not what it is saying because there are actual
effects in the material world of the fact that we're living in the Messianic Age.
And they're not just any effects.
They're the ones talked about in the Old Testament prophetic passages we read.
So a big one to me, at least, being not a Jewish person, is what we saw repeated in several
of those quotes about the knowledge of God covering the earth as the waters cover the sea.
No man having to teach his neighbor, no the Lord, no Yahweh.
because all will know him from the greatest to the least. Right. Let's talk about the reality.
When those words were said, who was there who knew the name Yahweh? Yeah, not that. And worshiped him.
Not many. Right. This tiny group, the time Jeremiah talked about it, they're on their way
into exile in Babylon. They've just been conquered and had their temple burned down.
So it's looking even worse at that point. Right. This tiny group at a backwater,
I love you.
heard of and the rest of the world, the rest of humanity is worshiping demons. Yeah.
Is engaged in idolatry, concomitant sexual immorality. Right. As I've said before, my ancestors were
painting themselves blue, dancing around fires, sacrificing members of neighboring tribes to demons
and probably eating them. Right. That's what my ancestors were doing at that time. That Jeremiah said
that right.
Herodotus said that mine were werewolves.
No, there you go.
I'm not even kidding.
Well, he said what he said was, he said that people who went up there said that they
were that he didn't believe it.
He said, but they all say it.
Yeah.
So, right, this is the reality.
And now you look at today, you can go almost anywhere in the world and say the word God,
capital G.
Right.
Right?
If it's an atheist, they're going to think of some kind of caricature of the God of the Bible.
Of the Christian Bible. That's the God they don't believe in.
I mean, they'll also say they don't believe in Zeus, but they're not really thinking about Zeus when they say they don't believe in God.
Right?
You know, billions of people. Right? And we, we, you know, I, as an Orthodox Christian, think a lot of them are
are
worshiping God the wrong way, right or misunderstand who he is or are completely wrong about who he is, right?
but
Muslims out there are at least trying to worship the God of Abraham. They're doing it wrong
They don't understand who he is because they don't understand who Christ is, right? But that's what they're trying to do
They're not trying to worship idols anymore
anymore. Right? And if you believe St. John of Damascus, they're basically
in Harrison, right? And here it takes kind of better than pagans, right? There has been a transformation.
Right? There has been a radical transformation. We haven't experienced it in our own life maybe,
but in world history there has been. And it's not just on that religious level of how people
think about God and the ceasing of idolatry.
Right. Right.
Idolatry is now in a tiny in tiny corners of the world.
Right.
It's supposed to everywhere.
That this has been a transformation of the very way we view ourselves
in each other and society.
Yeah. I mean, it's notable that even some of the most
vocally anti-Christian people in our society
are often being anti-Christian on the basis of Christian ethics.
Yes.
you know, essentially that Christians don't live up to their own end.
ethical code is what it comes down to be. Yeah, yeah. They challenge Christianity by their
firm belief in the concept of human rights. Yeah, right. That everybody is fundamentally equal
before God is not a pre-Christian idea. Yes. Right. And the things that I mean, go read Tom Holland's
dominion, right? Like, there's been this huge radical transformation of the way women are viewed
of the way we view other
human beings of the way we view sexuality, of the way we view morality, the way we view
the value of human life, has been utterly transformed by the spread of Christianity, even
amongst those who are not only non-Christian but anti-Christian.
Yeah, even in the whole countries in the world that are not Christian and never were Christian.
There's Christian ethics has affected them.
Yeah.
And this isn't just something that we can now, 2000 years later, look back.
and say, right, say Paul was already saying this, say Paul said, Christ is a savior of all men,
especially those who believe, especially those who are faithful, right? Christ having the authority,
all authority in heaven and on earth, rather than demonic powers, that benefits everyone.
That benefits the the virulent atheist, right?
As much as it benefits.
the person who holds to a non-Christian religion, right?
Benefits Christians a bit more, right?
Obviously, as St. Paul says, right?
More than a bit. But, right?
But this transformation of the world, the world now
in the messianic age, since Christ's ascension in the Throne meant,
is ordered fundamentally differently than it was before.
And if you study the ancient world in ancient history,
like Tom Holland who's not a Christian did. It's smack.
you in the face, right? It smacks you in the face. So by saying that Christ is right now
ruling from the right hand of the Father in heaven. Again, this is not, it's an ephemeral
or spiritualized or allegorical kind of kingdom. It's very literal. And it's over the invisible
and visible creations and it has concrete effects in the material world as well as the spiritual
Yeah. So I thought for a while about what I would say at the end, because there's so many
different directions that one could take with a lot of what we said. Last time I kind of
spent a little time saying, you know, dispensationalism is not good for you. One of the things that
I like to talk about a lot because I think it's really needed these days is this question
of hope.
A lot of times Christians look around us and we see that there's a lot of bad stuff going
on in the world and we might feel hopeless.
We might quote some of those lines from the Psalms, you know, how long, Lord, how long, right?
And some of they feel particularly hopeless might be tempted by the arguments that essentially
say,
This is all just pretend.
This is all just pretend you guys you've been calling out to your God for thousands of years and he still has not showed up.
I mean, this is a basic kind of apologetic against Christianity.
And it's tempting right it's tempting to accept that idea.
But the only way that that's really acceptable is
is with a very, very fundamental myopia
about the history of humanity.
And what do I mean by that?
Well, especially here in 21st century America,
our sense of history is,
I'm not gonna say it's zero, but it's approaching zero.
You know, I've had the opportunity
Thank you.
God to get to go to some places where you can't hardly kick a rock and not find an archaeological
side of some kind, you know. And a lot of other places in the world have a much deeper sense of
their own history. But the modern world in general is kind of arranged to make that harder,
but I think even more in America than probably most other places in the world.
So myopia is the default history.
myopia is the default way that we function. And even within our own, even within the scope of our own lives, we often, the way that I feel today is, is how I think about my life.
Right.
But if we take a step back, and we see that we are living in this millennium of the Messianic Age of Christ,
Messy and a gauge of Christ, that's a little redundant, but you know what I mean.
This is the period where Christ is ruling.
And we see like Father Stephen was just saying,
we look at the historical reality of how things were 2000
plus years ago versus how they are now.
There's this radical change in the world.
I'm not saying that things are great.
Again, it says in Scripture in the midst of his enemies.
So the enemies are still here.
They're not as not all here.
Lots of gone.
lots are defeated, lots have been kicked out and sent into the abyss.
So we can expect that there's still going to be bad stuff.
But nonetheless, the world is a very, very different place than it used to be.
And when we zoom back into our own lives
and assess where would I be without Christ?
How would I even understand life without Christ?
Then
we begin to see that his ruling in the midst of his enemies is not a reality that's just kind of on a
grand scale in the scope of human history or a grand in the scope of geography across the whole planet,
but it is within my life as well.
Right? That if he's ruling in the midst of his enemies, then I should expect also if I'm gonna be with Christ to be in the midst of his enemies.
So I should expect my life to include
demonic attack. I mean the Lord said in this world, you'll have trouble.
But he also said, be of good cheer, for I have overcome the world.
So that fundamental victory has been won.
And so what's happening now is the enemies in retreat, they're sacking their burning
as they go, but they've been routed and they're being chased down by the saints.
On behalf of Christ, Christ is doing this in them.
And so art.
task is to participate in that, not to just feel and feel bad and to complain often, right?
Or maybe even to give ourselves to despair that we are experiencing trouble.
That our hope is fundamentally not just thinking, well, you know, things are bad, but maybe
it'll get better someday, whatever.
But our hope is actually in our participation in
the work of Christ to cleanse this world from demonic influence, to bring about his order
and beauty and justice and love and kindness and all of these things, his ministry that we
are to be participants in his ministry, and that the more that we are faithful, then the
more that our hope grows.
I mean, that's just, that's the way that it works.
So when we talk about the millennium,
when we talk about the Messianic Age,
it's not just so we can make big charts
to put on the wall and say, ah, this is how it's all laid out.
I mean, I love maps and charts and stuff,
but that's not what it's about.
It's fundamentally about having the perspective
that we need in order to be faithful to do his work
in the places where we are and to participate
participate in his putting all of his enemies.
under his feet and going into all the world preaching the gospel, baptizing,
teaching everyone to do all that he has commanded. Father? So part of the reason,
honestly the main reason, I wanted to go through all that saner and airstuff,
was not just so I could do the neat trick of like.
everything you think you know about
St. Hernandez is wrong.
Ta-da, he's not a Kiles.
I mean, that was a little bit,
but that's not the main reason.
The main reason is that I think by working through that,
hopefully it's kind of made plain that Kiles
and it's sort of distant cousin modern pre-volualism
is not really a satisfactory answer to Nazism.
Because as we sort of talked about, it's kind of based on the same principles.
It's based on this principle of setting the material world and the good things in it and the enjoyment of it over against the spiritual world and spiritual things.
And saying one is more real or more important than the other.
All right.
It also...
has an additional problem over against the Nostya Kishu, and that problem is that the good things of
this world and the enjoyment of their of are pushed off into the future, not now but someday. And
this is part of what lies behind the comparison I made between the millennium and a Kilesh and an
makes it Kelli Eskiem and sort of Muslim heaven.
It's one of the features of...
of heaven in Islam is that suddenly you're allowed to indulge in all kinds of things that are
sinful when you're alive on earth.
Can't regalcohol when you're alive on earth, but all of a sudden, all the wine you want,
right, in paradise, etc., etc.
And there are shades of that, right, in Kiles.
That, again, points to a shared, sort of,
nostic view of asceticism.
That asceticism is denying yourself the world
because not because of trading something good for something
better, but because it's not really good.
Right.
But maybe it will become good in some later phase,
in some later world, in some later age,
or at least you'll be given permission
with that context.
to do, but otherwise you would not be permitted to do.
I think one of the importance is if we really embrace the truth of the fact that we are living
in the Messianic Age.
We are living in that age in which the Holy Spirit has been poured out upon all flesh.
We are members of the new covenant who have been grafted in a Saint Paul talks about as
Christian.
that that means that all of that imagery and all of those promises
of richness and abundance and peace and enjoyment.
All of those are ours for the claiming.
The church, the Orthodox church,
is not just about fasting, it's also about feasting.
It's not just about denial,
But it's also about
acceptance of one another. It's not just about going off by yourself into the wilderness
to pray, but it's also about the monastic who does go off by himself into the wilderness
to pray and draw close to God and come to know Christ deeply, throwing open the doors of
his monastic self to receive visitors and to pass on the wisdom and the sanctification
that he's received.
the holiness he's received, those who come to visit him and who need it.
And I think it's very easy because I've seen it on the faces of a lot of folks, especially
do the Orthodox folks, to think that Orthodoxy is about being very serious and very even
and dour, and about fasting even more than is required.
holding yourself apart from other people and about not laughing, right? And about not enjoying
yourself, right? And joy, of course, is a fruit of the Spirit. God has given us the good things
in the blessings of this world for us to enjoy and to receive with prayer and thanksgiving
and to share with each other. He's given us each other not just, right? Sometimes we talk about
about this. We talk about how well we live.
a community and so that means we rub up against each other and we bounce off each other
and we knock off each other's sharp edges. This is true, but also to enjoy each other.
To form friendships and bonds and familial relationships,
right, with each other. That are deep and important and are lasting and that will last for
eternity, not just for this life. St. Paul, who is talking about the resurrection in 1 Corinthians,
says
that if we have the hope of Christ only in this life,
meaning if there is no resurrection and we only have the hope of Christ of this life,
we of all men should be very much pity.
But what's interesting is, sometimes I think that we,
while we firmly believe in the resurrection of life of the world to come,
and we're looking forward to that, and our hopes are put in that,
Sometimes I think we don't really have the hope of Christ in this life.
anymore. We've kind of given up on it. We've just accepted this life in this world is going
to be available of tears. And I need to endure to the end. Right? And then there is joy,
and then there is happiness and everything in Christ afterwards. I'm not saying there
isn't all of those things afterwards, but all of those things are available to us here
and now.
St. Paul was in prison in
Philippi.
shackled to the ground in a pile of mud and feces,
and he was singing hymns and praising God.
He was not bitterly enduring.
He was not, you know, biting his lip and emoting.
He was not being stoic.
He was rejoicing.
How often, De St. Paul, read Philippians.
You can read it one sitting very easily.
I
I know someone who memorized the whole thing.
How many times does the St. Paul call on us to rejoice?
To rejoice in the Lord, to rejoice in each other,
to rejoice in the salvation we received?
I think we need to take seriously
that this is the Messianic Age.
We need to take feasting with each other,
with each other, not gluttony, not over drinking, right?
But with each other, feasting with each other
you
enjoying each other as seriously as we take fasting.
At least as seriously as we take our fasts and as we take
lent. We take Paska and the whole Paska season is seriously
as we take lent to the Wednesdays.
And I think when we do that, we'll see just how bad and error
it is to protect all of that joy and that fellowship and that
communion with each other.
out into the future as if it's not available to us now.
And we'll truly start to understand what it means to rejoice in the Lord
and to participate and experience our membership in the kingdom
of our Lord Jesus Christ and His reign over us and over our world.
Amen. Amen. Well, that is our show for tonight.
Thank you for the
listening everyone. If you didn't get through to us live, we'd still like to hear from you.
You can email us at LordofSpiritsandAncientFeed.com. Send me that hate mail that Father Stevens
is always talking about. You can also message us at our Facebook page, or you can leave us
a voice mail at SpeakPipe.com slash LordofSpirits.
Join us for our live broadcast of the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m.
Eastern, 4 p.m. Pacific, I smell blood, and an era of prominent madmen.
It's your own Facebook, follow our page, join our discussion group.
We review and ratings everywhere, but more importantly, share this show with a friend
whom you know is going to love it.
And oh, by the way, our conference has sold out.
There's a waiting list though.
We sell out.
And finally, be sure to go to extrafaith.com, stroke support, and help make sure we have lots
of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
For the thing I greatly feared is come upon me.
And what I dreaded has happened to me.
I am not a dees nor am I quiet.
I have no rest for trouble comes.
Thank you, good night.
God bless you.
and I feel fine.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient
faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne, and the beasts,
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000, and thousands of thousands,
with a loud voice.
voice worthy is the land that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom and strength
and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11-12.